<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="tsvn-introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_ABOUT"?>
	<simplesect>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>version control</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Version control is the art of managing changes to
			information. It has long been a critical tool for programmers,
			who typically spend their time making small changes to software
			and then undoing or checking some of those changes the next day.  
			Imagine a team of such developers working concurrently - and perhaps even
			simultaneously on the very same files! - and you can see why
			a good system is needed to <emphasis>manage the potential chaos</emphasis>.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-intro-about">
		<title>What is TortoiseGit?</title>
		<para>
			TortoiseGit is a free open-source client for the
			<firstterm>Subversion</firstterm> version control system.
			That is, TortoiseGit manages files and directories over time.
			Files are stored in a central <firstterm>repository</firstterm>.
			The repository is much like an ordinary file server, except that it
			remembers every change ever made to your files and directories.
			This allows you to recover older versions of your files and examine
			the history of how and when your data changed, and who changed it.
			This is why many people think of Subversion and version control
			systems in general as a sort of <quote>time machine</quote>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Some version control systems are also software configuration
			management (SCM) systems.  These systems are specifically
			tailored to manage trees of source code, and have many features
			that are specific to software development - such as natively
			understanding programming languages, or supplying tools for
			building software.  Subversion, however, is not one of these
			systems; it is a general system that can be used to manage
			<emphasis>any</emphasis> collection of files, including
			source code.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-intro-history">
		<title>TortoiseGit's History</title>
		<para>
			In 2002, Tim Kemp found that Subversion was a very good version
			control system, but it lacked a good GUI client. The idea for a
			Subversion client as a Windows shell integration was inspired by
			the similar client for CVS named TortoiseCVS.
		</para>
		<para>
			Tim studied the source code of TortoiseCVS and used it as a base for
			TortoiseGit. He then started the project, registered the domain
			<literal>TortoiseGit.org</literal> and put the source code online. During that time,
			Stefan Küng was looking for a good and free version control system
			and found Subversion and the source for TortoiseGit. Since TortoiseGit
			was still not ready for use then he joined the project and started
			programming. Soon he rewrote most of the existing code and started
			adding commands and features, up to a point where nothing of the
			original code remained.
		</para>
		<para>
			As Subversion became more stable it attracted more and more users
			who also started using TortoiseGit as their Subversion client.
			The user base grew quickly (and is still growing every day).
			That's when Lübbe Onken offered to help out with some nice icons
			and a logo for TortoiseGit. And he takes care of the website
			and manages the translation.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-intro-features">
		<title>TortoiseGit's Features</title>
		<para>
			What makes TortoiseGit such a good Subversion client?
			Here's a short list of features.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Shell integration</term>
				<listitem>
					<indexterm>
						<primary>Windows shell</primary>
					</indexterm>
					<indexterm>
						<primary>explorer</primary>
					</indexterm>
					<para>
						TortoiseGit integrates seamlessly into the Windows shell
						(i.e. the explorer). This means you can keep working
						with the tools you're already familiar with. And you
						do not have to change into a different application
						each time you need functions of the version control!
					</para>
					<para>
						And you are not even forced to use the Windows Explorer.
						TortoiseGit's context menus work in many other file managers,
						and in the File/Open dialog which is common to most
						standard Windows applications.
						You should, however, bear in mind that TortoiseGit
						is intentionally developed as extension for the Windows
						Explorer. Thus it is possible that in other applications
						the integration is not as complete and e.g. the icon
						overlays may not be shown.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Icon overlays</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The status of every versioned file and folder is
						indicated by small overlay icons. That way you can see
						right away what the status of your working copy is.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Easy access to Subversion commands</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						All Subversion commands are available from the explorer
						context menu. TortoiseGit adds its own submenu there.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			Since TortoiseGit is a Subversion client, we would also like to show you
			some of the features of Subversion itself:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Directory versioning</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						CVS only tracks the history of individual files, but
						Subversion implements a <quote>virtual</quote>
						versioned filesystem that tracks changes to whole
						directory trees over time.
						Files <emphasis>and</emphasis> directories are
						versioned. As a result, there are real client-side
						<command>move</command> and <command>copy</command>
						commands that operate on files and directories.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Atomic commits</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A commit either goes into the repository completely,
						or not at all.  This allows developers to construct and
						commit changes as logical chunks.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Versioned metadata</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Each file and directory has an invisible set of
						<quote>properties</quote> attached. You can invent and
						store any arbitrary key/value pairs you wish.
						Properties are versioned over time, just like file
						contents.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Choice of network layers</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subversion has an abstracted notion of repository
						access, making it easy for people to implement new
						network mechanisms. Subversion's <quote>advanced</quote>
						network server is a module for the Apache web server,
						which speaks a variant of HTTP called WebDAV/DeltaV.
						This gives Subversion a big advantage in stability and
						interoperability, and provides various key features for
						free: authentication, authorization, wire compression,
						and repository browsing, for example. A smaller,
						standalone Subversion server process is also available.
						This server speaks a custom protocol which can be
						easily tunneled over ssh.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Consistent data handling</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subversion expresses file differences using a binary
						differencing algorithm, which works identically on both
						text (human-readable) and binary (human-unreadable) files.
						Both types of files are stored equally compressed in the
						repository, and differences are transmitted in both
						directions across the network.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Efficient branching and tagging</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The cost of branching and tagging need not be
						proportional to the project size. Subversion creates
						branches and tags by simply copying the project, using
						a mechanism similar to a hard-link.
						Thus these operations take only a very small,
						constant amount of time, and very little space in the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Hackability</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subversion has no historical baggage; it is implemented
						as a collection of shared C libraries with well-defined
						APIs. This makes Subversion extremely maintainable and
						usable by other applications and languages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-intro-install">
		<title>Installing TortoiseGit</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>System requirements</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseGit runs on Windows 2000 SP2, Windows XP or higher.
				Windows 98, Windows ME and Windows NT4 are no longer supported
				since TortoiseGit 1.2.0, but you can still download
				the older versions if you really need them.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you encounter any problems during or after installing
				TortoiseGit please refer to
				<xref linkend="tsvn-faq"/>
				first.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Installation</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>install</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				TortoiseGit comes with an easy to use installer. Double click on
				the installer file and follow the instructions. The installer
				will take care of the rest. 
			</para>
			<important>
				<para>
					You need Administrator privileges to install TortoiseGit.
				</para>
			</important>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-intro-install-lang">
			<title>Language Packs</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>language packs</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>translations</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				The TortoiseGit user interface has been translated into many
				different languages, so you may be able to download a language
				pack to suit your needs.
				You can find the language packs on our 
				<ulink url="http://TortoiseGit.net/translation_status">
					<citetitle>translation status page</citetitle>
				</ulink>.
				And if there is no language pack available yet, why not join
				the team and submit your own translation ;-)
			</para>
			<para>
				Each language pack is packaged as a <literal>.exe</literal> installer.
				Just run the install program and follow the instructions.
				Next time you restart, the translation will be available.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-intro-install-spell">
			<title>Spellchecker</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>spellchecker</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>dictionary</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				TortoiseGit includes a spell checker which allows you to check your
				commit log messages. This is especially useful if the project language
				is not your native language.
				The spell checker uses the same dictionary files as
				<ulink url="http://openoffice.org">
					<citetitle>OpenOffice</citetitle>
				</ulink>
				and 
				<ulink url="http://mozilla.org">
					<citetitle>Mozilla</citetitle>
				</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The installer automatically adds the US and UK English dictionaries.
				If you want other languages, the easiest option is simply to
				install one of TortoiseGit's language packs. This will install
				the appropriate dictionary files as well as the TortoiseGit local
				user interface.
				Next time you restart, the dictionary will be available too.
			</para>
			<para>
				Or you can install the dictionaries yourself. If you have OpenOffice or
				Mozilla installed, you can copy those dictionaries, which are located
				in the installation folders for those applications.
				Otherwise, you need to download the required dictionary files from
				<ulink url="http://wiki.services.openoffice.org/wiki/Dictionaries">
					<citetitle>http://wiki.services.openoffice.org/wiki/Dictionaries</citetitle>
				</ulink>
			</para>
			<para>
				Once you have got the dictionary files, you
				probably need to rename them so that the filenames only have
				the locale chars in it.
				Example:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<filename>en_US.aff</filename>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<filename>en_US.dic</filename>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				Then just copy them to the <filename>bin</filename> sub-folder of
				the TortoiseGit installation folder. Normally this will be
				<filename>C:\Program Files\TortoiseGit\bin</filename>.
				If you don't want to litter the <filename>bin</filename> sub-folder,
				you can instead place your spell checker files in
				<filename>C:\Program Files\TortoiseGit\Languages</filename>. If that folder isn't
				there, you have to create it first.
				The next time you start TortoiseGit, the spell checker will be available.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you install multiple dictionaries, TortoiseGit uses these rules
				to select which one to use.
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Check the <literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> setting.
						Refer to <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage"/> for information
						about setting project properties.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						If no project language is set, or that language is not
						installed, try the language corresponding to the Windows locale.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						If the exact Windows locale doesn't work, try the
						<quote>Base</quote> language, eg.
						<literal>de_CH</literal> (Swiss-German) falls back to
						<literal>de_DE</literal> (German).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						If none of the above works, then the default language
						is English, which is included with the standard installation.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
