<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<appendix id="tgit-ibugtraqprovider">
	<title>IBugTraqProvider interface</title>
	<simplesect>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>plugin</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>IBugTraqProvider</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>COM</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>issue tracker</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			To get a tighter integration with issue trackers than by simply
			using the <literal>bugtraq.</literal> config keys, TortoiseGit can make use of COM
			plugins. With such plugins it is possible to fetch information
			directly from the issue tracker, interact with the user and provide
			information back to TortoiseGit about open issues, verify log
			messages entered by the user and even run actions after a successful
			commit to e.g, close an issue.
		</para>
		<para>
			We can't provide information and tutorials on how you have
			to implement a COM object in your preferred programming language, but
			we have example plugins in C++/ATL and C# in our repository in
			the <filename>contrib/issue-tracker-plugins</filename> folder.
			In that folder you can also find the required include files you
			need to build your plugin.
			(<xref linkend="tgit-preface-source"/> explains how to access the repository.)
		</para>
		<important>
			<para>
				You should provide both a 32-bit and 64-bit version of your
				plugin. Because the x64-Version of TortoiseGit cannot use a 32-bit
				plugin and vice-versa.
			</para>
		</important>
	</simplesect>
	<sect1 id="tgit-bugtraqnaming">
		<title>Naming conventions</title>
		<para>
			If you release an issue tracker plugin for Tortoise*-clients, please do
			<emphasis>not</emphasis> name it <emphasis>Tortoise&lt;Something&gt;</emphasis>.
			We'd like to reserve the <emphasis>Tortoise</emphasis> prefix for a version control
			client integrated into the windows shell. For example: TortoiseCVS, TortoiseSVN,
			TortoiseHg, TortoiseGit and TortoiseBzr are all version control clients.
		</para>
		<para>
			Please name your plugin for a Tortoise client <emphasis>Turtle&lt;Something&gt;</emphasis>,
			where <emphasis>&lt;Something&gt;</emphasis> refers to the issue tracker that you are connecting to.
			Alternatively choose a name that sounds like <emphasis>Turtle</emphasis> but has
			a different first letter. Nice examples are:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Gurtle - An issue tracker plugin for Google code</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>TurtleMine - An issue tracker plugin for Redmine</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>VurtleOne - An issue tracker plugin for VersionOne</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tgit-ibugtraqprovider-1">
		<title>The IBugTraqProvider interface</title>
		<para>
			TortoiseGit 1.2.1 and later can use plugins which implement the IBugTraqProvider
			interface. The interface provides a few methods which plugins can
			use to interact with the issue tracker.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT ValidateParameters (
  // Parent window for any UI that needs to be
  // displayed during validation.
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // The parameter string that needs to be validated.
  [in] BSTR parameters,

  // Is the string valid?
  [out, retval] VARIANT_BOOL *valid
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called from the settings dialog where the user can
			add and configure the plugin. The <literal>parameters</literal> string
			can be used by a plugin to get additional required information, e.g., the URL
			to the issue tracker, login information, etc.
			The plugin should verify the <literal>parameters</literal> string and
			show an error dialog if the string is not valid. The <literal>hParentWnd</literal>
			parameter should be used for any dialog the plugin shows as the parent window.
			The plugin must return TRUE if the validation of the <literal>parameters</literal>
			string is successful. If the plugin returns FALSE, the settings dialog won't
			allow the user to add the plugin to a working copy path.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT GetLinkText (
  // Parent window for any (error) UI that needs to be displayed.
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // The parameter string, just in case you need to talk to your
  // web service (e.g.) to find out what the correct text is.
  [in] BSTR parameters,

  // What text do you want to display?
  // Use the current thread locale.
  [out, retval] BSTR *linkText
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			The plugin can provide a string here which is used in the TortoiseGit
			commit dialog for the button which invokes the plugin, e.g., "Choose issue"
			or "Select ticket". Make sure the string is not too long, otherwise it
			might not fit into the button.
			If the method returns an error (e.g., <literal>E_NOTIMPL</literal>), a default
			text is used for the button.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT GetCommitMessage (
  // Parent window for your provider's UI.
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // Parameters for your provider.
  [in] BSTR parameters,
  [in] BSTR commonRoot,
  [in] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) pathList,

  // The text already present in the commit message.
  // Your provider should include this text in the new message,
  // where appropriate.
  [in] BSTR originalMessage,

  // The new text for the commit message.
  // This replaces the original message.
  [out, retval] BSTR *newMessage
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This is the main method of the plugin. This method is called from
			the TortoiseGit commit dialog when the user clicks on the plugin
			button.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>parameters</literal> string is the string the
			user has to enter in the settings dialog when he configures
			the plugin. Usually a plugin would use this to find the URL
			of the issue tracker and/or login information or more.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>commonRoot</literal> string contains the parent path
			of all items selected to bring up the commit dialog. Note that this
			is <emphasis>not</emphasis> the root path of all items which the user has selected in
			the commit dialog.
			For the branch/tag dialog, this is the path which is to be copied.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>pathList</literal> parameter contains an array of paths
			(as strings) which the user has selected for the commit.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>originalMessage</literal> parameter contains the text
			entered in the log message box in the commit dialog. If the user
			has not yet entered any text, this string will be empty.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>newMessage</literal> return string is copied into
			the log message edit box in the commit dialog, replacing whatever
			is already there. If a plugin does not modify the <literal>originalMessage</literal>
			string, it must return the same string again here, otherwise
			any text the user has entered will be lost.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tgit-ibugtraqprovider-2">
		<title>The IBugTraqProvider2 interface</title>
		<para>
			In TortoiseSVN 1.6 a new interface was added which provides
			more functionality for plugins (also available in TortoiseGit since 1.2.1). This IBugTraqProvider2 interface
			inherits from IBugTraqProvider.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT GetCommitMessage2 (
  // Parent window for your provider's UI.
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // Parameters for your provider.
  [in] BSTR parameters,
  // The common URL of the commit
  [in] BSTR commonURL,
  [in] BSTR commonRoot,
  [in] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) pathList,

  // The text already present in the commit message.
  // Your provider should include this text in the new message,
  // where appropriate.
  [in] BSTR originalMessage,

  // You can assign custom revision properties to a commit
  // by setting the next two params.
  // note: Both safearrays must be of the same length.
  //       For every property name there must be a property value!

  // The content of the bugID field (if shown)
  [in] BSTR bugID,

  // Modified content of the bugID field
  [out] BSTR * bugIDOut,

  // The list of revision property names.
  [out] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) * revPropNames,

  // The list of revision property values.
  [out] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) * revPropValues,

  // The new text for the commit message.
  // This replaces the original message
  [out, retval] BSTR * newMessage
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called from the TortoiseGit commit dialog
			when the user clicks on the plugin button. This method is called
			instead of <literal>GetCommitMessage()</literal>. Please refer
			to the documentation for <literal>GetCommitMessage</literal>
			for the parameters that are also used there.
		</para>
		<para>
			The parameter <literal>commonURL</literal> is the parent URL
			of all items selected to bring up the commit dialog. This is basically
			the URL of the <literal>commonRoot</literal> path.
		</para>
		<para>
			The parameter <literal>bugID</literal> contains the content of
			the bug-ID field (if it is shown, configured with the property
			<literal>bugtraq.message</literal>).
		</para>
		<para>
			The return parameter <literal>bugIDOut</literal> is used to fill
			the bug-ID field when the method returns.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>revPropNames</literal> and <literal>revPropValues</literal>
			are only honored by TortoiseSVN and are ignored by TortoiseGit.
			If no revision properties are to be set, the plugin must return empty arrays.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT CheckCommit (
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,
  [in] BSTR parameters,
  [in] BSTR commonURL,
  [in] BSTR commonRoot,
  [in] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) pathList,
  [in] BSTR commitMessage,
  [out, retval] BSTR * errorMessage
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called right before the commit dialog is closed
			and the commit begins. A plugin can use this method to validate
			the selected files/folders for the commit and/or the commit
			message entered by the user. The parameters are the same as
			for <literal>GetCommitMessage2()</literal>, with the difference that
			<literal>commonURL</literal> is now the common URL of all
			<emphasis>checked</emphasis> items, and <literal>commonRoot</literal>
			the root path of all checked items.
		</para>
		<para>
			For the branch/tag dialog, the <literal>commonURL</literal> is the source
			URL of the copy, and <literal>commonRoot</literal> is set to the
			target URL of the copy.
		</para>
		<para>
			The return parameter <literal>errorMessage</literal> must
			either contain an error message which TortoiseGit shows to the
			user or be empty for the commit to start.
			If an error message is returned, TortoiseGit shows the error
			string in a dialog and keeps the commit dialog open so the
			user can correct whatever is wrong. A plugin should therefore
			return an error string which informs the user <emphasis>what</emphasis>
			is wrong and how to correct it.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT  OnCommitFinished (
  // Parent window for any (error) UI that needs to be displayed.
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // The common root of all paths that got committed.
  [in] BSTR commonRoot,

  // All the paths that got committed.
  [in] SAFEARRAY(BSTR) pathList,


  // The text already present in the commit message.
  [in] BSTR logMessage,

  // The revision of the commit.
  [in] ULONG revision,


  // An error to show to the user if this function
  // returns something else than S_OK
  [out, retval] BSTR * error
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called after a successful commit. A plugin
			can use this method to e.g., close the selected issue or add
			information about the commit to the issue.
			The parameters are the same as for <literal>GetCommitMessage2</literal>.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT HasOptions(
  // Whether the provider provides options
  [out, retval] VARIANT_BOOL *ret
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called from the settings dialog where the user
			can configure the plugins. If a plugin provides its own
			configuration dialog with <literal>ShowOptionsDialog</literal>, it must
			return TRUE here, otherwise it must return FALSE.
		</para>
<programlisting>
HRESULT ShowOptionsDialog(
  // Parent window for the options dialog
  [in] HWND hParentWnd,

  // Parameters for your provider.
  [in] BSTR parameters,

  // The parameters string
  [out, retval] BSTR * newparameters
);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This method is called from the settings dialog when the user
			clicks on the "Options" button that is shown if <literal>HasOptions</literal>
			returns TRUE.
			A plugin can show an options dialog to make it easier for the user
			to configure the plugin.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>parameters</literal> string contains the plugin
			parameters string that is already set/entered.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>newparameters</literal> return parameter must contain
			the parameters string which the plugin constructed from the info
			it gathered in its options dialog. That <literal>paramameters</literal>
			string is passed to all other IBugTraqProvider and IBugTraqProvider2
			methods.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
