<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<appendix id="tsvn-ssh-howto">
	<title>Securing Svnserve using SSH</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
			This section provides a step-by-step guide to setting up
			Git and TortoiseGit to use the <literal>svn+ssh</literal>
			protocol. If you already use authenticated SSH connections to login
			to your server, then you are already there and you can find more detail
			in the Git book. If you are not using SSH but would like to do
			so to protect your Git installation, this guide gives a simple
			method which does not involve creating a separate SSH user account
			on the server for every Git user.
		</para>
		<para>
			In this implementation we create a single SSH user account for
			all Git users, and use different authentication keys to
			differentiate between the real Git users.
		</para>
		<para>
			In this appendix we assume that you already have the Git tools
			installed, and that you have created a repository as detailed elsewhere
			in this manual. Note that you should <emphasis>not</emphasis> start
			svnserve as a service or daemon when used with SSH.
		</para>
		<para>
			Much of the information here comes from a tutorial
			provided by Marc Logemann, which can be found at
			<ulink url="http://www.logemann.org/2007/03/13/Git-TortoiseGit-ssh-howto/">
				<citetitle>www.logemann.org</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			Additional information on setting up a Windows server was
			provided by Thorsten Müller. Thanks guys!
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-linux-server">
		<title>Setting Up a Linux Server</title>
		<para>
			You need to have SSH enabled on the server, and here we assume
			that you will be using OpenSSH. On most distributions this will
			already be installed. To find out, type:
<screen>
ps xa | grep sshd
</screen>
			and look for ssh jobs.
		</para>
		<para>
			One point to note is that if you build Git from source and
			do not provide any argument to <filename>./configure</filename>,
			Git creates a <filename>bin</filename> directory under
			<filename>/usr/local</filename> and places its binaries there.
			If you want to use tunneling mode with SSH, you have to be aware
			that the user logging in via SSH needs to execute the svnserve program 
			and some other binaries. For this reason, either place 
			<filename>/usr/local/bin</filename> into the <literal>PATH</literal> variable 
			or create symbolic links of your binaries to the <filename>/usr/sbin</filename>
			directory, or to any other directory which is commonly in the
			<literal>PATH</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			To check that everything is OK, login in as the target user with SSH
			and type:
<screen>
which svnserve
</screen>
			This command should tell you if svnserve is reachable.
		</para>
		<para>
			Create a new user which we will use to access the svn repository:
<screen>
useradd -m svnuser
</screen>
			Be sure to give this user full access rights to the repository.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-windows-server">
		<title>Setting Up a Windows Server</title>
		<para>
			Install Cygwin SSH daemon as described here: 
			<ulink url="http://pigtail.net/LRP/printsrv/cygwin-sshd.html">
				<citetitle>http://pigtail.net/LRP/printsrv/cygwin-sshd.html</citetitle>
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<para>
			Create a new Windows user account <literal>svnuser</literal> which
			we will use to access the repository.
			Be sure to give this user full access rights to the repository.
		</para>
		<para>
			If there is no password file yet then create one from the Cygwin console using:
<screen>
mkpasswd -l > /etc/passwd
</screen>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-client-tools">
		<title>SSH Client Tools for use with TortoiseGit</title>
		<para>
			Grab the tools we need for using SSH on the windows client from this site:
			<ulink url="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/">
				<citetitle>http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			Just go to the download section and get
			<filename>Putty</filename>,
			<filename>Plink</filename>,
			<filename>Pageant</filename> and
			<filename>Puttygen</filename>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-create-keys">
		<title>Creating OpenSSH Certificates</title>
		<para>
			The next step is to create a key pair for authentication.
			There are two possible ways to create keys. The first is to 
			create the keys with PuTTYgen on the client, upload the public
			key to your server and use the private key with PuTTY.
			The other is to create the key pair with the OpenSSH tool
			ssh-keygen, download the private key to your client and
			convert the private key to a PuTTY-style private key.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-ssh-create-ssh-keygen">
			<title>Create Keys using ssh-keygen</title>
			<para>
				Login to the server as <literal>root</literal> or
				<literal>svnuser</literal> and type:
<screen>
ssh-keygen -b 1024 -t dsa -N passphrase -f keyfile
</screen>
				substituting a real pass-phrase (which only you know) and key file.
				We just created a SSH2 DSA key with 1024 bit key-phrase.
				If you type
<screen>
ls -l keyfile*
</screen>
				you will see two files, <filename>keyfile</filename> and
				<filename>keyfile.pub</filename>. As you might guess, the
				<filename>.pub</filename> file is the public key file, the
				other is the private one.
			</para>
			<para>
				Append the public key to those in the <filename>.ssh</filename>
				folder within the <literal>svnuser</literal> home directory:
<screen>
cat keyfile.pub &gt;&gt; /home/svnuser/.ssh/authorized_keys
</screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				In order to use the private key we generated, we have to
				convert it to a putty format. This is because the private
				key file format is not specified by a standards body.
				After you download the private key file to your client PC,
				start PuTTYgen and use
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Conversions</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Import key</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				Browse to your file <filename>keyfile</filename> which you got
				from the server the passphrase you used when creating the key.
				Finally click on <guibutton>Save private key</guibutton> and
				save the file as <filename>keyfile.PPK</filename>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-ssh-create-puttygen">
			<title>Create Keys using PuTTYgen</title>
			<para>
				Use PuTTYgen to generate a public-key/private-key pair and
				save it. Copy the public key to the server and append it to
				those in the <filename>.ssh</filename> folder within the
				<literal>svnuser</literal> home directory:
<screen>
cat keyfile.pub &gt;&gt; /home/svnuser/.ssh/authorized_keys
</screen>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-test-putty">
		<title>Test using PuTTY</title>
		<para>
			To test the connection we will use PuTTY. Start the program and
			on the <guilabel>Session</guilabel> tab set the hostname to
			the name or IP address of your server, the protocol to SSH and
			save the session as <literal>SvnConnection</literal> or whatever
			name you prefer. On the <guilabel>SSH</guilabel> tab set the
			preferred SSH protocol version to 2 and from <guilabel>Auth</guilabel>
			set the full path to the <literal>.PPK</literal> private key file you
			converted earlier.
			Go back to the <guilabel>Sessions</guilabel> tab and hit the
			<guilabel>Save</guilabel> button. You will now see
			<literal>SvnConnection</literal> in the list of saved sessions.
		</para>
		<para>
			Click on <guilabel>Open</guilabel> and you should see a telnet
			style login prompt. Use <literal>svnuser</literal> as the user name
			and if all is well you should connect directly without being
			prompted for a password.
		</para>
		<para>
			You may need to edit <filename>/etc/sshd_config</filename> on the
			server. Edit lines as follows and restart the SSH service afterwards.
<screen>
PubkeyAuthentication yes
PasswordAuthentication no
PermitEmptyPasswords no
ChallengeResponseAuthentication no
</screen>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-testing-tsvn">
		<title>Testing SSH with TortoiseGit</title>
		<para>
			So far we have only tested that you can login using SSH. Now we need
			to make sure that the SSH connection can actually run svnserve.
			On the server modify <filename>/home/svnuser/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>
			as follows to allow many Git authors to use the same system account,
			<literal>svnuser</literal>. Note that every Git author uses the same
			login but a different authentication key, thus you have to add one line for
			every author.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note: This is all on one very long line.
<screen>
command="svnserve -t -r &lt;ReposRootPath&gt; --tunnel-user=&lt;author&gt;",
            no-port-forwarding,no-agent-forwarding,no-X11-forwarding,
            no-pty ssh-rsa &lt;PublicKey&gt; &lt;Comment&gt;
</screen>
			There are several values that you need to set according to your setup.
		</para>
		<para>
			<literal>&lt;ReposRootPath&gt;</literal> should be replaced with the
			path to the directory containing your repositories. This avoids the
			need to specify full server paths within URLs. Note that you must use
			forward slashes even on a Windows server, e.g.
			<filename>c:/svn/reposroot</filename>. In the examples below we assume
			that you have a repository folder within the repository root called
			<filename>repos</filename>.
		</para>
		<para>
			<literal>&lt;author&gt;</literal> should be replaced with the svn author
			that you want to be stored on commit. This also allows svnserve to use
			its own access rights within <filename>svnserve.conf</filename>.
		</para>
		<para>
			<literal>&lt;PublicKey&gt;</literal> should be replaced with the 
			public key that you generated earlier.
		</para>
		<para>
			<literal>&lt;Comment&gt;</literal> can be any comment you like, but it is
			useful for mapping an svn author name to the person's real name.
		</para>
		<para>
			Right click on any folder in Windows Explorer and select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Repo-Browser</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You will be prompted to enter a URL, so enter one in this form:
<screen>
svn+ssh://svnuser@SvnConnection/repos
</screen>
			What does this URL mean? The Schema name is <literal>svn+ssh</literal>
			which tells TortoiseGit how to handle the requests to the server. 
			After the double slash, you specify the user to connect to the server,
			in our case <literal>svnuser</literal>. After the <literal>@</literal>
			we supply our PuTTY session name. 
			This session name contains all details like where to find 
			the private key and the server's IP or DNS. Lastly we have to 
			provide the path to the repository, relative to the repository root
			on the server, as specified in the <filename>authorized_keys</filename> file.
		</para>
		<para>
			Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and you should be able to browse
			the repository content. If so you now have a running SSH tunnel in 
			conjunction with TortoiseGit.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that by default TortoiseGit uses its own version of Plink to
			connect. This avoids a console window popping up for every authentication
			attempt, but it also means that there is nowhere for error messages to
			appear. If you receive the error <quote>Unable to write to standard output</quote>,
			you can try specifying Plink as the client in TortoiseGit's network settings.
			This will allow you to see the real error message generated by Plink.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-configvariants">
		<title>SSH Configuration Variants</title>
		<para>
			One way to simplify the URL in TortoiseGit is to set the 
			user inside the PuTTY session. For this you have to load 
			your already defined session <literal>SvnConnection</literal>
			in PuTTY and in the <guilabel>Connection</guilabel> tab set
			<guilabel>Auto login user</guilabel> to the user name, e.g.
			<literal>svnuser</literal>. Save your PuTTY session as before
			and try the following URL inside TortoiseGit:
<screen>
svn+ssh://SvnConnection/repos
</screen>
			This time we only provide the PuTTY session <literal>SvnConnection</literal>
			to the SSH client TortoiseGit uses (TortoisePlink.exe). 
			This client will check the session for all necessary details.
		</para>
		<para>
			At the time of writing PuTTY does not check all saved configurations,
			so if you have multiple configurations with the same server name, it
			will pick the first one which matches. Also, if you edit the default
			configuration and save it, the auto login user name is
			<emphasis>not</emphasis> saved.
		</para>
		<para>
			Many people like to use Pageant for storing all their keys.
			Because a PuTTY session is capable of storing a key, you don't
			always need Pageant. But imagine you want to store keys for several 
			different servers; in that case you would have to edit the
			PuTTY session over and over again, depending on the server you are 
			trying to connect with. In this situation Pageant makes perfect sense,
			because when PuTTY, Plink, TortoisePlink or any other PuTTY-based tool
			is trying to connect to an SSH server, it checks all private keys that
			Pageant holds to initiate the connection.
		</para>
		<para>
			For this task, simply run Pageant and add the private key. It should
			be the same private key you defined in the PuTTY session above.
			If you use Pageant for private key storage, you can delete the reference
			to the private key file in your saved PuTTY session.
			You can add more keys for other servers, or other users of course.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you don't want to repeat this procedure after every reboot of your 
			client, you should place Pageant in the auto-start group of your
			Windows installation. You can append the keys with 
			complete paths as command line arguments to Pageant.exe
		</para>
		<para>
			The last way to connect to an SSH server is simply by using this URL
			inside TortoiseGit:
<screen>
svn+ssh://svnuser@100.101.102.103/repos
svn+ssh://svnuser@mydomain.com/repos
</screen>
			As you can see, we don't use a saved PuTTY session but an IP address
			(or domain name) as the connection target. We also supply the user, 
			but you might ask how the private key file will be found. 
			Because TortoisePlink.exe is just a modified version of the standard
			Plink tool from the PuTTY suite, TortoiseGit will also try all the keys
			stored in Pageant.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you use this last method, be sure you do not have a default username
			set in PuTTY. We have had reports of a bug in PuTTY causing connections
			to close in this case. To remove the default user, simply clear
			<filename>HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\SimonTatham\Putty\Sessions\Default%20Settings\HostName</filename>
		</para>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
