<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-mv(1)">
    <title>git-mv(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-mv(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-mv - Move or rename a file, a directory, or a symlink</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git mv</emphasis> &lt;options&gt;&#8230; &lt;args&gt;&#8230;</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Move or rename a file, directory or symlink.</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">git mv [-v] [-f] [-n] [-k] &lt;source&gt; &lt;destination&gt;
git mv [-v] [-f] [-n] [-k] &lt;source&gt; ... &lt;destination directory&gt;</literallayout>
<simpara>In the first form, it renames &lt;source&gt;, which must exist and be either
a file, symlink or directory, to &lt;destination&gt;.
In the second form, the last argument has to be an existing
directory; the given sources will be moved into this directory.</simpara>
<simpara>The index is updated after successful completion, but the change must still be
committed.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-f
</term>
<term>
--force
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Force renaming or moving of a file even if the target exists
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-k
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Skip move or rename actions which would lead to an error
        condition. An error happens when a source is neither existing nor
        controlled by Git, or when it would overwrite an existing
        file unless <emphasis>-f</emphasis> is given.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-n
</term>
<term>
--dry-run
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Do nothing; only show what would happen
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-v
</term>
<term>
--verbose
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Report the names of files as they are moved.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__submodules">
<title>SUBMODULES</title>
<simpara>Moving a submodule using a gitfile (which means they were cloned
with a Git version 1.7.8 or newer) will update the gitfile and
core.worktree setting to make the submodule work in the new location.
It also will attempt to update the submodule.&lt;name&gt;.path setting in
the <xref linkend="gitmodules(5)" /> file and stage that file (unless -n is used).</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__bugs">
<title>BUGS</title>
<simpara>Each time a superproject update moves a populated submodule (e.g. when
switching between commits before and after the move) a stale submodule
checkout will remain in the old location and an empty directory will
appear in the new location. To populate the submodule again in the new
location the user will have to run "git submodule update"
afterwards. Removing the old directory is only safe when it uses a
gitfile, as otherwise the history of the submodule will be deleted
too. Both steps will be obsolete when recursive submodule update has
been implemented.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-mv(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
