<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-push(1)">
    <title>git-push(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-push(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-push - Update remote refs along with associated objects</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git push</emphasis> [--all | --mirror | --tags] [--follow-tags] [--atomic] [-n | --dry-run] [--receive-pack=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;]
           [--repo=&lt;repository&gt;] [-f | --force] [-d | --delete] [--prune] [-v | --verbose]
           [-u | --set-upstream]
           [--[no-]signed|--sign=(true|false|if-asked)]
           [--force-with-lease[=&lt;refname&gt;[:&lt;expect&gt;]]]
           [--no-verify] [&lt;repository&gt; [&lt;refspec&gt;&#8230;]]</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Updates remote refs using local refs, while sending objects
necessary to complete the given refs.</simpara>
<simpara>You can make interesting things happen to a repository
every time you push into it, by setting up <emphasis>hooks</emphasis> there.  See
documentation for <xref linkend="git-receive-pack(1)" />.</simpara>
<simpara>When the command line does not specify where to push with the
<emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis> argument, <emphasis>branch.*.remote</emphasis> configuration for the
current branch is consulted to determine where to push.  If the
configuration is missing, it defaults to <emphasis>origin</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>When the command line does not specify what to push with <emphasis>&lt;refspec&gt;...</emphasis>
arguments or <emphasis>--all</emphasis>, <emphasis>--mirror</emphasis>, <emphasis>--tags</emphasis> options, the command finds
the default <emphasis>&lt;refspec&gt;</emphasis> by consulting <emphasis>remote.*.push</emphasis> configuration,
and if it is not found, honors <emphasis>push.default</emphasis> configuration to decide
what to push (See <xref linkend="git-config(1)" /> for the meaning of <emphasis>push.default</emphasis>).</simpara>
<simpara>When neither the command-line nor the configuration specify what to
push, the default behavior is used, which corresponds to the <emphasis>simple</emphasis>
value for <emphasis>push.default</emphasis>: the current branch is pushed to the
corresponding upstream branch, but as a safety measure, the push is
aborted if the upstream branch does not have the same name as the
local one.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__options_anchor_id_git_push_1__options_xreflabel_options">
<title>OPTIONS<anchor id="git-push(1)_OPTIONS" xreflabel="[OPTIONS]"/></title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;repository&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The "remote" repository that is destination of a push
        operation.  This parameter can be either a URL
        (see the section <link linkend="git-push(1)_URLS">GIT URLS</link> below) or the name
        of a remote (see the section <link linkend="git-push(1)_REMOTES">REMOTES</link> below).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;refspec&gt;&#8230;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Specify what destination ref to update with what source object.
        The format of a &lt;refspec&gt; parameter is an optional plus
        <emphasis>+</emphasis>, followed by the source object &lt;src&gt;, followed
        by a colon <emphasis>:</emphasis>, followed by the destination ref &lt;dst&gt;.
</simpara>
<simpara>The &lt;src&gt; is often the name of the branch you would want to push, but
it can be any arbitrary "SHA-1 expression", such as <emphasis>master~4</emphasis> or
<emphasis>HEAD</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="gitrevisions(7)" />).</simpara>
<simpara>The &lt;dst&gt; tells which ref on the remote side is updated with this
push. Arbitrary expressions cannot be used here, an actual ref must
be named.
If <emphasis>git push [&lt;repository&gt;]</emphasis> without any <emphasis>&lt;refspec&gt;</emphasis> argument is set to
update some ref at the destination with <emphasis>&lt;src&gt;</emphasis> with
<emphasis>remote.&lt;repository&gt;.push</emphasis> configuration variable, <emphasis>:&lt;dst&gt;</emphasis> part can
be omitted--such a push will update a ref that <emphasis>&lt;src&gt;</emphasis> normally updates
without any <emphasis>&lt;refspec&gt;</emphasis> on the command line.  Otherwise, missing
<emphasis>:&lt;dst&gt;</emphasis> means to update the same ref as the <emphasis>&lt;src&gt;</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>The object referenced by &lt;src&gt; is used to update the &lt;dst&gt; reference
on the remote side.  By default this is only allowed if &lt;dst&gt; is not
a tag (annotated or lightweight), and then only if it can fast-forward
&lt;dst&gt;.  By having the optional leading <emphasis>+</emphasis>, you can tell Git to update
the &lt;dst&gt; ref even if it is not allowed by default (e.g., it is not a
fast-forward.)  This does <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> attempt to merge &lt;src&gt; into &lt;dst&gt;.  See
EXAMPLES below for details.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis>tag &lt;tag&gt;</emphasis> means the same as <emphasis>refs/tags/&lt;tag&gt;:refs/tags/&lt;tag&gt;</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>Pushing an empty &lt;src&gt; allows you to delete the &lt;dst&gt; ref from
the remote repository.</simpara>
<simpara>The special refspec <emphasis>:</emphasis> (or <emphasis>+:</emphasis> to allow non-fast-forward updates)
directs Git to push "matching" branches: for every branch that exists on
the local side, the remote side is updated if a branch of the same name
already exists on the remote side.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--all
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Push all branches (i.e. refs under <emphasis>refs/heads/</emphasis>); cannot be
        used with other &lt;refspec&gt;.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--prune
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Remove remote branches that don't have a local counterpart. For example
        a remote branch <emphasis>tmp</emphasis> will be removed if a local branch with the same
        name doesn't exist any more. This also respects refspecs, e.g.
        <emphasis>git push --prune remote refs/heads/*:refs/tmp/*</emphasis> would
        make sure that remote <emphasis>refs/tmp/foo</emphasis> will be removed if <emphasis>refs/heads/foo</emphasis>
        doesn't exist.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--mirror
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Instead of naming each ref to push, specifies that all
        refs under <emphasis>refs/</emphasis> (which includes but is not
        limited to <emphasis>refs/heads/</emphasis>, <emphasis>refs/remotes/</emphasis>, and <emphasis>refs/tags/</emphasis>)
        be mirrored to the remote repository.  Newly created local
        refs will be pushed to the remote end, locally updated refs
        will be force updated on the remote end, and deleted refs
        will be removed from the remote end.  This is the default
        if the configuration option <emphasis>remote.&lt;remote&gt;.mirror</emphasis> is
        set.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-n
</term>
<term>
--dry-run
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Do everything except actually send the updates.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--porcelain
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Produce machine-readable output.  The output status line for each ref
        will be tab-separated and sent to stdout instead of stderr.  The full
        symbolic names of the refs will be given.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--delete
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        All listed refs are deleted from the remote repository. This is
        the same as prefixing all refs with a colon.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--tags
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        All refs under <emphasis>refs/tags</emphasis> are pushed, in
        addition to refspecs explicitly listed on the command
        line.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--follow-tags
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Push all the refs that would be pushed without this option,
        and also push annotated tags in <emphasis>refs/tags</emphasis> that are missing
        from the remote but are pointing at commit-ish that are
        reachable from the refs being pushed.  This can also be specified
        with configuration variable <emphasis>push.followTags</emphasis>.  For more
        information, see <emphasis>push.followTags</emphasis> in <xref linkend="git-config(1)" />.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]signed
</term>
<term>
--sign=(true|false|if-asked)
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        GPG-sign the push request to update refs on the receiving
        side, to allow it to be checked by the hooks and/or be
        logged.  If <emphasis>false</emphasis> or <emphasis>--no-signed</emphasis>, no signing will be
        attempted.  If <emphasis>true</emphasis> or <emphasis>--signed</emphasis>, the push will fail if the
        server does not support signed pushes.  If set to <emphasis>if-asked</emphasis>,
        sign if and only if the server supports signed pushes.  The push
        will also fail if the actual call to <emphasis>gpg --sign</emphasis> fails.  See
        <xref linkend="git-receive-pack(1)" /> for the details on the receiving end.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]atomic
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use an atomic transaction on the remote side if available.
        Either all refs are updated, or on error, no refs are updated.
        If the server does not support atomic pushes the push will fail.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--receive-pack=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;
</term>
<term>
--exec=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Path to the <emphasis>git-receive-pack</emphasis> program on the remote
        end.  Sometimes useful when pushing to a remote
        repository over ssh, and you do not have the program in
        a directory on the default $PATH.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]force-with-lease
</term>
<term>
--force-with-lease=&lt;refname&gt;
</term>
<term>
--force-with-lease=&lt;refname&gt;:&lt;expect&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Usually, "git push" refuses to update a remote ref that is
        not an ancestor of the local ref used to overwrite it.
</simpara>
<simpara>This option overrides this restriction if the current value of the
remote ref is the expected value.  "git push" fails otherwise.</simpara>
<simpara>Imagine that you have to rebase what you have already published.
You will have to bypass the "must fast-forward" rule in order to
replace the history you originally published with the rebased history.
If somebody else built on top of your original history while you are
rebasing, the tip of the branch at the remote may advance with her
commit, and blindly pushing with <emphasis>--force</emphasis> will lose her work.</simpara>
<simpara>This option allows you to say that you expect the history you are
updating is what you rebased and want to replace. If the remote ref
still points at the commit you specified, you can be sure that no
other people did anything to the ref. It is like taking a "lease" on
the ref without explicitly locking it, and the remote ref is updated
only if the "lease" is still valid.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis>--force-with-lease</emphasis> alone, without specifying the details, will protect
all remote refs that are going to be updated by requiring their
current value to be the same as the remote-tracking branch we have
for them.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis>--force-with-lease=&lt;refname&gt;</emphasis>, without specifying the expected value, will
protect the named ref (alone), if it is going to be updated, by
requiring its current value to be the same as the remote-tracking
branch we have for it.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis>--force-with-lease=&lt;refname&gt;:&lt;expect&gt;</emphasis> will protect the named ref (alone),
if it is going to be updated, by requiring its current value to be
the same as the specified value &lt;expect&gt; (which is allowed to be
different from the remote-tracking branch we have for the refname,
or we do not even have to have such a remote-tracking branch when
this form is used).</simpara>
<simpara>Note that all forms other than <emphasis>--force-with-lease=&lt;refname&gt;:&lt;expect&gt;</emphasis>
that specifies the expected current value of the ref explicitly are
still experimental and their semantics may change as we gain experience
with this feature.</simpara>
<simpara>"--no-force-with-lease" will cancel all the previous --force-with-lease on the
command line.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-f
</term>
<term>
--force
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Usually, the command refuses to update a remote ref that is
        not an ancestor of the local ref used to overwrite it.
        Also, when <emphasis>--force-with-lease</emphasis> option is used, the command refuses
        to update a remote ref whose current value does not match
        what is expected.
</simpara>
<simpara>This flag disables these checks, and can cause the remote repository
to lose commits; use it with care.</simpara>
<simpara>Note that <emphasis>--force</emphasis> applies to all the refs that are pushed, hence
using it with <emphasis>push.default</emphasis> set to <emphasis>matching</emphasis> or with multiple push
destinations configured with <emphasis>remote.*.push</emphasis> may overwrite refs
other than the current branch (including local refs that are
strictly behind their remote counterpart).  To force a push to only
one branch, use a <emphasis>+</emphasis> in front of the refspec to push (e.g <emphasis>git push
origin +master</emphasis> to force a push to the <emphasis>master</emphasis> branch). See the
<emphasis>&lt;refspec&gt;...</emphasis> section above for details.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--repo=&lt;repository&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        This option is equivalent to the &lt;repository&gt; argument. If both
        are specified, the command-line argument takes precedence.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-u
</term>
<term>
--set-upstream
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        For every branch that is up to date or successfully pushed, add
        upstream (tracking) reference, used by argument-less
        <xref linkend="git-pull(1)" /> and other commands. For more information,
        see <emphasis>branch.&lt;name&gt;.merge</emphasis> in <xref linkend="git-config(1)" />.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]thin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        These options are passed to <xref linkend="git-send-pack(1)" />. A thin transfer
        significantly reduces the amount of sent data when the sender and
        receiver share many of the same objects in common. The default is
        --thin.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-q
</term>
<term>
--quiet
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Suppress all output, including the listing of updated refs,
        unless an error occurs. Progress is not reported to the standard
        error stream.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-v
</term>
<term>
--verbose
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Run verbosely.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--progress
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Progress status is reported on the standard error stream
        by default when it is attached to a terminal, unless -q
        is specified. This flag forces progress status even if the
        standard error stream is not directed to a terminal.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--no-recurse-submodules
</term>
<term>
--recurse-submodules=check|on-demand|no
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        May be used to make sure all submodule commits used by the
        revisions to be pushed are available on a remote-tracking branch.
        If <emphasis>check</emphasis> is used Git will verify that all submodule commits that
        changed in the revisions to be pushed are available on at least one
        remote of the submodule. If any commits are missing the push will
        be aborted and exit with non-zero status. If <emphasis>on-demand</emphasis> is used
        all submodules that changed in the revisions to be pushed will be
        pushed. If on-demand was not able to push all necessary revisions
        it will also be aborted and exit with non-zero status. A value of
        <emphasis>no</emphasis> or using <emphasis>--no-recurse-submodules</emphasis> can be used to override the
        push.recurseSubmodules configuration variable when no submodule
        recursion is required.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]verify
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Toggle the pre-push hook (see <xref linkend="githooks(5)" />).  The
        default is --verify, giving the hook a chance to prevent the
        push.  With --no-verify, the hook is bypassed completely.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-4
</term>
<term>
--ipv4
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use IPv4 addresses only, ignoring IPv6 addresses.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-6
</term>
<term>
--ipv6
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use IPv6 addresses only, ignoring IPv4 addresses.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__git_urls_anchor_id_git_push_1__urls_xreflabel_urls">
<title>GIT URLS<anchor id="git-push(1)_URLS" xreflabel="[URLS]"/></title>
<simpara>In general, URLs contain information about the transport protocol, the
address of the remote server, and the path to the repository.
Depending on the transport protocol, some of this information may be
absent.</simpara>
<simpara>Git supports ssh, git, http, and https protocols (in addition, ftp,
and ftps can be used for fetching, but this is inefficient and
deprecated; do not use it).</simpara>
<simpara>The native transport (i.e. git:// URL) does no authentication and
should be used with caution on unsecured networks.</simpara>
<simpara>The following syntaxes may be used with them:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
ssh://&#91;user@&#93;host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
git://host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
http&#91;s&#93;://host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
ftp&#91;s&#93;://host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>An alternative scp-like syntax may also be used with the ssh protocol:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
&#91;user@&#93;host.xz:path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>This syntax is only recognized if there are no slashes before the
first colon. This helps differentiate a local path that contains a
colon. For example the local path <emphasis>foo:bar</emphasis> could be specified as an
absolute path or <emphasis>./foo:bar</emphasis> to avoid being misinterpreted as an ssh
url.</simpara>
<simpara>The ssh and git protocols additionally support ~username expansion:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
ssh://&#91;user@&#93;host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/~&#91;user&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
git://host.xz&#91;:port&#93;/~&#91;user&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
&#91;user@&#93;host.xz:/~&#91;user&#93;/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>For local repositories, also supported by Git natively, the following
syntaxes may be used:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
/path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
file:///path/to/repo.git/
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>These two syntaxes are mostly equivalent, except when cloning, when
the former implies --local option. See <xref linkend="git-clone(1)" /> for
details.</simpara>
<simpara>When Git doesn't know how to handle a certain transport protocol, it
attempts to use the <emphasis>remote-&lt;transport&gt;</emphasis> remote helper, if one
exists. To explicitly request a remote helper, the following syntax
may be used:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
&lt;transport&gt;::&lt;address&gt;
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>where &lt;address&gt; may be a path, a server and path, or an arbitrary
URL-like string recognized by the specific remote helper being
invoked. See <xref linkend="gitremote-helpers(1)" /> for details.</simpara>
<simpara>If there are a large number of similarly-named remote repositories and
you want to use a different format for them (such that the URLs you
use will be rewritten into URLs that work), you can create a
configuration section of the form:</simpara>
<screen>        [url "&lt;actual url base&gt;"]
                insteadOf = &lt;other url base&gt;</screen>
<simpara>For example, with this:</simpara>
<screen>        [url "git://git.host.xz/"]
                insteadOf = host.xz:/path/to/
                insteadOf = work:</screen>
<simpara>a URL like "work:repo.git" or like "host.xz:/path/to/repo.git" will be
rewritten in any context that takes a URL to be "git://git.host.xz/repo.git".</simpara>
<simpara>If you want to rewrite URLs for push only, you can create a
configuration section of the form:</simpara>
<screen>        [url "&lt;actual url base&gt;"]
                pushInsteadOf = &lt;other url base&gt;</screen>
<simpara>For example, with this:</simpara>
<screen>        [url "ssh://example.org/"]
                pushInsteadOf = git://example.org/</screen>
<simpara>a URL like "git://example.org/path/to/repo.git" will be rewritten to
"ssh://example.org/path/to/repo.git" for pushes, but pulls will still
use the original URL.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__remotes_anchor_id_git_push_1__remotes_xreflabel_remotes">
<title>REMOTES<anchor id="git-push(1)_REMOTES" xreflabel="[REMOTES]"/></title>
<simpara>The name of one of the following can be used instead
of a URL as <emphasis>&lt;repository&gt;</emphasis> argument:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
a remote in the Git configuration file: <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/config</emphasis>,
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
a file in the <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/remotes</emphasis> directory, or
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
a file in the <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/branches</emphasis> directory.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>All of these also allow you to omit the refspec from the command line
because they each contain a refspec which git will use by default.</simpara>
<section id="git-push(1)__named_remote_in_configuration_file">
<title>Named remote in configuration file</title>
<simpara>You can choose to provide the name of a remote which you had previously
configured using <xref linkend="git-remote(1)" />, <xref linkend="git-config(1)" />
or even by a manual edit to the <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/config</emphasis> file.  The URL of
this remote will be used to access the repository.  The refspec
of this remote will be used by default when you do
not provide a refspec on the command line.  The entry in the
config file would appear like this:</simpara>
<screen>        [remote "&lt;name&gt;"]
                url = &lt;url&gt;
                pushurl = &lt;pushurl&gt;
                push = &lt;refspec&gt;
                fetch = &lt;refspec&gt;</screen>
<simpara>The <emphasis>&lt;pushurl&gt;</emphasis> is used for pushes only. It is optional and defaults
to <emphasis>&lt;url&gt;</emphasis>.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="git-push(1)__named_file_in_emphasis_git_dir_remotes_emphasis">
<title>Named file in <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/remotes</emphasis></title>
<simpara>You can choose to provide the name of a
file in <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/remotes</emphasis>.  The URL
in this file will be used to access the repository.  The refspec
in this file will be used as default when you do not
provide a refspec on the command line.  This file should have the
following format:</simpara>
<screen>        URL: one of the above URL format
        Push: &lt;refspec&gt;
        Pull: &lt;refspec&gt;</screen>
<simpara><emphasis>Push:</emphasis> lines are used by <emphasis>git push</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Pull:</emphasis> lines are used by <emphasis>git pull</emphasis> and <emphasis>git fetch</emphasis>.
Multiple <emphasis>Push:</emphasis> and <emphasis>Pull:</emphasis> lines may
be specified for additional branch mappings.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="git-push(1)__named_file_in_emphasis_git_dir_branches_emphasis">
<title>Named file in <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/branches</emphasis></title>
<simpara>You can choose to provide the name of a
file in <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/branches</emphasis>.
The URL in this file will be used to access the repository.
This file should have the following format:</simpara>
<screen>        &lt;url&gt;#&lt;head&gt;</screen>
<simpara><emphasis>&lt;url&gt;</emphasis> is required; <emphasis>#&lt;head&gt;</emphasis> is optional.</simpara>
<simpara>Depending on the operation, git will use one of the following
refspecs, if you don't provide one on the command line.
<emphasis>&lt;branch&gt;</emphasis> is the name of this file in <emphasis>$GIT_DIR/branches</emphasis> and
<emphasis>&lt;head&gt;</emphasis> defaults to <emphasis>master</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>git fetch uses:</simpara>
<screen>        refs/heads/&lt;head&gt;:refs/heads/&lt;branch&gt;</screen>
<simpara>git push uses:</simpara>
<screen>        HEAD:refs/heads/&lt;head&gt;</screen>
</section>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__output">
<title>OUTPUT</title>
<simpara>The output of "git push" depends on the transport method used; this
section describes the output when pushing over the Git protocol (either
locally or via ssh).</simpara>
<simpara>The status of the push is output in tabular form, with each line
representing the status of a single ref. Each line is of the form:</simpara>
<screen> &lt;flag&gt; &lt;summary&gt; &lt;from&gt; -&gt; &lt;to&gt; (&lt;reason&gt;)</screen>
<simpara>If --porcelain is used, then each line of the output is of the form:</simpara>
<screen> &lt;flag&gt; \t &lt;from&gt;:&lt;to&gt; \t &lt;summary&gt; (&lt;reason&gt;)</screen>
<simpara>The status of up-to-date refs is shown only if --porcelain or --verbose
option is used.</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
flag
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        A single character indicating the status of the ref:
</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
(space)
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a successfully pushed fast-forward;
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>+</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a successful forced update;
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>-</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a successfully deleted ref;
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>*</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a successfully pushed new ref;
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>!</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a ref that was rejected or failed to push; and
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>=</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
for a ref that was up to date and did not need pushing.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
summary
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        For a successfully pushed ref, the summary shows the old and new
        values of the ref in a form suitable for using as an argument to
        <emphasis>git log</emphasis> (this is <emphasis>&lt;old&gt;..&lt;new&gt;</emphasis> in most cases, and
        <emphasis>&lt;old&gt;...&lt;new&gt;</emphasis> for forced non-fast-forward updates).
</simpara>
<simpara>For a failed update, more details are given:</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
rejected
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Git did not try to send the ref at all, typically because it
        is not a fast-forward and you did not force the update.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
remote rejected
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The remote end refused the update.  Usually caused by a hook
        on the remote side, or because the remote repository has one
        of the following safety options in effect:
        <emphasis>receive.denyCurrentBranch</emphasis> (for pushes to the checked out
        branch), <emphasis>receive.denyNonFastForwards</emphasis> (for forced
        non-fast-forward updates), <emphasis>receive.denyDeletes</emphasis> or
        <emphasis>receive.denyDeleteCurrent</emphasis>.  See <xref linkend="git-config(1)" />.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
remote failure
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The remote end did not report the successful update of the ref,
        perhaps because of a temporary error on the remote side, a
        break in the network connection, or other transient error.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
from
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The name of the local ref being pushed, minus its
        <emphasis>refs/&lt;type&gt;/</emphasis> prefix. In the case of deletion, the
        name of the local ref is omitted.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
to
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The name of the remote ref being updated, minus its
        <emphasis>refs/&lt;type&gt;/</emphasis> prefix.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
reason
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        A human-readable explanation. In the case of successfully pushed
        refs, no explanation is needed. For a failed ref, the reason for
        failure is described.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__note_about_fast_forwards">
<title>Note about fast-forwards</title>
<simpara>When an update changes a branch (or more in general, a ref) that used to
point at commit A to point at another commit B, it is called a
fast-forward update if and only if B is a descendant of A.</simpara>
<simpara>In a fast-forward update from A to B, the set of commits that the original
commit A built on top of is a subset of the commits the new commit B
builds on top of.  Hence, it does not lose any history.</simpara>
<simpara>In contrast, a non-fast-forward update will lose history.  For example,
suppose you and somebody else started at the same commit X, and you built
a history leading to commit B while the other person built a history
leading to commit A.  The history looks like this:</simpara>
<screen>      B
     /
 ---X---A</screen>
<simpara>Further suppose that the other person already pushed changes leading to A
back to the original repository from which you two obtained the original
commit X.</simpara>
<simpara>The push done by the other person updated the branch that used to point at
commit X to point at commit A.  It is a fast-forward.</simpara>
<simpara>But if you try to push, you will attempt to update the branch (that
now points at A) with commit B.  This does <emphasis>not</emphasis> fast-forward.  If you did
so, the changes introduced by commit A will be lost, because everybody
will now start building on top of B.</simpara>
<simpara>The command by default does not allow an update that is not a fast-forward
to prevent such loss of history.</simpara>
<simpara>If you do not want to lose your work (history from X to B) or the work by
the other person (history from X to A), you would need to first fetch the
history from the repository, create a history that contains changes done
by both parties, and push the result back.</simpara>
<simpara>You can perform "git pull", resolve potential conflicts, and "git push"
the result.  A "git pull" will create a merge commit C between commits A
and B.</simpara>
<screen>      B---C
     /   /
 ---X---A</screen>
<simpara>Updating A with the resulting merge commit will fast-forward and your
push will be accepted.</simpara>
<simpara>Alternatively, you can rebase your change between X and B on top of A,
with "git pull --rebase", and push the result back.  The rebase will
create a new commit D that builds the change between X and B on top of
A.</simpara>
<screen>      B   D
     /   /
 ---X---A</screen>
<simpara>Again, updating A with this commit will fast-forward and your push will be
accepted.</simpara>
<simpara>There is another common situation where you may encounter non-fast-forward
rejection when you try to push, and it is possible even when you are
pushing into a repository nobody else pushes into. After you push commit
A yourself (in the first picture in this section), replace it with "git
commit --amend" to produce commit B, and you try to push it out, because
forgot that you have pushed A out already. In such a case, and only if
you are certain that nobody in the meantime fetched your earlier commit A
(and started building on top of it), you can run "git push --force" to
overwrite it. In other words, "git push --force" is a method reserved for
a case where you do mean to lose history.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__examples">
<title>Examples</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Works like <emphasis>git push &lt;remote&gt;</emphasis>, where &lt;remote&gt; is the
        current branch's remote (or <emphasis>origin</emphasis>, if no remote is
        configured for the current branch).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Without additional configuration, pushes the current branch to
        the configured upstream (<emphasis>remote.origin.merge</emphasis> configuration
        variable) if it has the same name as the current branch, and
        errors out without pushing otherwise.
</simpara>
<simpara>The default behavior of this command when no &lt;refspec&gt; is given can be
configured by setting the <emphasis>push</emphasis> option of the remote, or the <emphasis>push.default</emphasis>
configuration variable.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, to default to pushing only the current branch to <emphasis>origin</emphasis>
use <emphasis>git config remote.origin.push HEAD</emphasis>.  Any valid &lt;refspec&gt; (like
the ones in the examples below) can be configured as the default for
<emphasis>git push origin</emphasis>.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin :</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Push "matching" branches to <emphasis>origin</emphasis>. See
        &lt;refspec&gt; in the <link linkend="git-push(1)_OPTIONS">OPTIONS</link> section above for a
        description of "matching" branches.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin master</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Find a ref that matches <emphasis>master</emphasis> in the source repository
        (most likely, it would find <emphasis>refs/heads/master</emphasis>), and update
        the same ref (e.g. <emphasis>refs/heads/master</emphasis>) in <emphasis>origin</emphasis> repository
        with it.  If <emphasis>master</emphasis> did not exist remotely, it would be
        created.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin HEAD</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        A handy way to push the current branch to the same name on the
        remote.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push mothership master:satellite/master dev:satellite/dev</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use the source ref that matches <emphasis>master</emphasis> (e.g. <emphasis>refs/heads/master</emphasis>)
        to update the ref that matches <emphasis>satellite/master</emphasis> (most probably
        <emphasis>refs/remotes/satellite/master</emphasis>) in the <emphasis>mothership</emphasis> repository;
        do the same for <emphasis>dev</emphasis> and <emphasis>satellite/dev</emphasis>.
</simpara>
<simpara>This is to emulate <emphasis>git fetch</emphasis> run on the <emphasis>mothership</emphasis> using <emphasis>git
push</emphasis> that is run in the opposite direction in order to integrate
the work done on <emphasis>satellite</emphasis>, and is often necessary when you can
only make connection in one way (i.e. satellite can ssh into
mothership but mothership cannot initiate connection to satellite
because the latter is behind a firewall or does not run sshd).</simpara>
<simpara>After running this <emphasis>git push</emphasis> on the <emphasis>satellite</emphasis> machine, you would
ssh into the <emphasis>mothership</emphasis> and run <emphasis>git merge</emphasis> there to complete the
emulation of <emphasis>git pull</emphasis> that were run on <emphasis>mothership</emphasis> to pull changes
made on <emphasis>satellite</emphasis>.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin HEAD:master</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Push the current branch to the remote ref matching <emphasis>master</emphasis> in the
        <emphasis>origin</emphasis> repository. This form is convenient to push the current
        branch without thinking about its local name.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin master:refs/heads/experimental</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Create the branch <emphasis>experimental</emphasis> in the <emphasis>origin</emphasis> repository
        by copying the current <emphasis>master</emphasis> branch.  This form is only
        needed to create a new branch or tag in the remote repository when
        the local name and the remote name are different; otherwise,
        the ref name on its own will work.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin :experimental</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Find a ref that matches <emphasis>experimental</emphasis> in the <emphasis>origin</emphasis> repository
        (e.g. <emphasis>refs/heads/experimental</emphasis>), and delete it.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis>git push origin +dev:master</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Update the origin repository's master branch with the dev branch,
        allowing non-fast-forward updates.  <emphasis role="strong">This can leave unreferenced
        commits dangling in the origin repository.</emphasis>  Consider the
        following situation, where a fast-forward is not possible:
</simpara>
<screen>            o---o---o---A---B  origin/master
                     \
                      X---Y---Z  dev</screen>
<simpara>The above command would change the origin repository to</simpara>
<screen>                      A---B  (unnamed branch)
                     /
            o---o---o---X---Y---Z  master</screen>
<simpara>Commits A and B would no longer belong to a branch with a symbolic name,
and so would be unreachable.  As such, these commits would be removed by
a <emphasis>git gc</emphasis> command on the origin repository.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-push(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
