<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-send-pack(1)">
    <title>git-send-pack(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-send-pack(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-send-pack - Push objects over Git protocol to another repository</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git send-pack</emphasis> [--all] [--dry-run] [--force] [--receive-pack=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;]
                [--verbose] [--thin] [--atomic]
                [--[no-]signed|--sign=(true|false|if-asked)]
                [&lt;host&gt;:]&lt;directory&gt; [&lt;ref&gt;&#8230;]</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Usually you would want to use <emphasis>git push</emphasis>, which is a
higher-level wrapper of this command, instead. See <xref linkend="git-push(1)" />.</simpara>
<simpara>Invokes <emphasis>git-receive-pack</emphasis> on a possibly remote repository, and
updates it from the current repository, sending named refs.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--receive-pack=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Path to the <emphasis>git-receive-pack</emphasis> program on the remote
        end.  Sometimes useful when pushing to a remote
        repository over ssh, and you do not have the program in
        a directory on the default $PATH.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--exec=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Same as --receive-pack=&lt;git-receive-pack&gt;.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--all
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Instead of explicitly specifying which refs to update,
        update all heads that locally exist.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--stdin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Take the list of refs from stdin, one per line. If there
        are refs specified on the command line in addition to this
        option, then the refs from stdin are processed after those
        on the command line.
</simpara>
<simpara>If <emphasis>--stateless-rpc</emphasis> is specified together with this option then
the list of refs must be in packet format (pkt-line). Each ref must
be in a separate packet, and the list must end with a flush packet.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--dry-run
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Do everything except actually send the updates.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--force
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Usually, the command refuses to update a remote ref that
        is not an ancestor of the local ref used to overwrite it.
        This flag disables the check.  What this means is that
        the remote repository can lose commits; use it with
        care.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--verbose
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Run verbosely.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--thin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Send a "thin" pack, which records objects in deltified form based
        on objects not included in the pack to reduce network traffic.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--atomic
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use an atomic transaction for updating the refs. If any of the refs
        fails to update then the entire push will fail without changing any
        refs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--[no-]signed
</term>
<term>
--sign=(true|false|if-asked)
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        GPG-sign the push request to update refs on the receiving
        side, to allow it to be checked by the hooks and/or be
        logged.  If <emphasis>false</emphasis> or <emphasis>--no-signed</emphasis>, no signing will be
        attempted.  If <emphasis>true</emphasis> or <emphasis>--signed</emphasis>, the push will fail if the
        server does not support signed pushes.  If set to <emphasis>if-asked</emphasis>,
        sign if and only if the server supports signed pushes.  The push
        will also fail if the actual call to <emphasis>gpg --sign</emphasis> fails.  See
        <xref linkend="git-receive-pack(1)" /> for the details on the receiving end.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;host&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        A remote host to house the repository.  When this
        part is specified, <emphasis>git-receive-pack</emphasis> is invoked via
        ssh.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;directory&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The repository to update.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;ref&gt;&#8230;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The remote refs to update.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__specifying_the_refs">
<title>Specifying the Refs</title>
<simpara>There are three ways to specify which refs to update on the
remote end.</simpara>
<simpara>With <emphasis>--all</emphasis> flag, all refs that exist locally are transferred to
the remote side.  You cannot specify any <emphasis>&lt;ref&gt;</emphasis> if you use
this flag.</simpara>
<simpara>Without <emphasis>--all</emphasis> and without any <emphasis>&lt;ref&gt;</emphasis>, the heads that exist
both on the local side and on the remote side are updated.</simpara>
<simpara>When one or more <emphasis>&lt;ref&gt;</emphasis> are specified explicitly (whether on the
command line or via <emphasis>--stdin</emphasis>), it can be either a
single pattern, or a pair of such pattern separated by a colon
":" (this means that a ref name cannot have a colon in it).  A
single pattern <emphasis>&lt;name&gt;</emphasis> is just a shorthand for <emphasis>&lt;name&gt;:&lt;name&gt;</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>Each pattern pair consists of the source side (before the colon)
and the destination side (after the colon).  The ref to be
pushed is determined by finding a match that matches the source
side, and where it is pushed is determined by using the
destination side. The rules used to match a ref are the same
rules used by <emphasis>git rev-parse</emphasis> to resolve a symbolic ref
name. See <xref linkend="git-rev-parse(1)" />.</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
It is an error if &lt;src&gt; does not match exactly one of the
   local refs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
It is an error if &lt;dst&gt; matches more than one remote refs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
If &lt;dst&gt; does not match any remote ref, either
</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
it has to start with "refs/"; &lt;dst&gt; is used as the
     destination literally in this case.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
&lt;src&gt; == &lt;dst&gt; and the ref that matched the &lt;src&gt; must not
     exist in the set of remote refs; the ref matched &lt;src&gt;
     locally is used as the name of the destination.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>Without <emphasis>--force</emphasis>, the &lt;src&gt; ref is stored at the remote only if
&lt;dst&gt; does not exist, or &lt;dst&gt; is a proper subset (i.e. an
ancestor) of &lt;src&gt;.  This check, known as "fast-forward check",
is performed in order to avoid accidentally overwriting the
remote ref and lose other peoples' commits from there.</simpara>
<simpara>With <emphasis>--force</emphasis>, the fast-forward check is disabled for all refs.</simpara>
<simpara>Optionally, a &lt;ref&gt; parameter can be prefixed with a plus <emphasis>+</emphasis> sign
to disable the fast-forward check only on that ref.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-send-pack(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
