<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-hash-object(1)">
    <title>git-hash-object(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-hash-object(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-hash-object(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-hash-object - Compute object ID and optionally creates a blob from a file</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-hash-object(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git hash-object</emphasis> [-t &lt;type&gt;] [-w] [--path=&lt;file&gt;|--no-filters] [--stdin [--literally]] [--] &lt;file&gt;&#8230;
<emphasis>git hash-object</emphasis> [-t &lt;type&gt;] [-w] --stdin-paths [--no-filters]</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-hash-object(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Computes the object ID value for an object with specified type
with the contents of the named file (which can be outside of the
work tree), and optionally writes the resulting object into the
object database.  Reports its object ID to its standard output.
This is used by <emphasis>git cvsimport</emphasis> to update the index
without modifying files in the work tree.  When &lt;type&gt; is not
specified, it defaults to "blob".</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-hash-object(1)__options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-t &lt;type&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Specify the type (default: "blob").
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-w
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Actually write the object into the object database.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--stdin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Read the object from standard input instead of from a file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--stdin-paths
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Read file names from the standard input, one per line, instead
        of from the command-line.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--path
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Hash object as it were located at the given path. The location of
        file does not directly influence on the hash value, but path is
        used to determine what Git filters should be applied to the object
        before it can be placed to the object database, and, as result of
        applying filters, the actual blob put into the object database may
        differ from the given file. This option is mainly useful for hashing
        temporary files located outside of the working directory or files
        read from stdin.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--no-filters
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Hash the contents as is, ignoring any input filter that would
        have been chosen by the attributes mechanism, including the end-of-line
        conversion. If the file is read from standard input then this
        is always implied, unless the <emphasis>--path</emphasis> option is given.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--literally
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Allow <emphasis>--stdin</emphasis> to hash any garbage into a loose object which might not
        otherwise pass standard object parsing or git-fsck checks. Useful for
        stress-testing Git itself or reproducing characteristics of corrupt or
        bogus objects encountered in the wild.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-hash-object(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
