<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article lang="en" id="git-repack(1)">
<articleinfo>
    <title>git-repack(1)</title>
        <indexterm>
                <primary>git-repack(1)</primary>
        </indexterm>
</articleinfo>
<simplesect id="_name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-repack - Pack unpacked objects in a repository</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<simpara><emphasis>git repack</emphasis> [-a] [-A] [-d] [-f] [-l] [-n] [-q] [--window=N] [--depth=N]</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>This script is used to combine all objects that do not currently
reside in a "pack", into a pack.  It can also be used to re-organize
existing packs into a single, more efficient pack.</simpara>
<simpara>A pack is a collection of objects, individually compressed, with
delta compression applied, stored in a single file, with an
associated index file.</simpara>
<simpara>Packs are used to reduce the load on mirror systems, backup
engines, disk storage, etc.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-a
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Instead of incrementally packing the unpacked objects,
        pack everything referenced into a single pack.
        Especially useful when packing a repository that is used
        for private development and there is no need to worry
        about people fetching via dumb protocols from it.  Use
        with <emphasis>-d</emphasis>.  This will clean up the objects that <literal>git prune</literal>
        leaves behind, but <literal>git fsck --full</literal> shows as
        dangling.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-A
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Same as <literal>-a</literal>, unless <emphasis>-d</emphasis> is used.  Then any unreachable
        objects in a previous pack become loose, unpacked objects,
        instead of being left in the old pack.  Unreachable objects
        are never intentionally added to a pack, even when repacking.
        This option prevents unreachable objects from being immediately
        deleted by way of being left in the old pack and then
        removed.  Instead, the loose unreachable objects
        will be pruned according to normal expiry rules
        with the next <emphasis>git-gc</emphasis> invocation. See <xref linkend="git-gc(1)"/>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-d
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        After packing, if the newly created packs make some
        existing packs redundant, remove the redundant packs.
        Also run  <emphasis>git-prune-packed</emphasis> to remove redundant
        loose object files.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-l
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Pass the <literal>--local</literal> option to <emphasis>git-pack-objects</emphasis>. See
        <xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)"/>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-f
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Pass the <literal>--no-reuse-object</literal> option to <literal>git-pack-objects</literal>, see
        <xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)"/>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-q
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Pass the <literal>-q</literal> option to <emphasis>git-pack-objects</emphasis>. See
        <xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)"/>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-n
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Do not update the server information with
        <emphasis>git-update-server-info</emphasis>.  This option skips
        updating local catalog files needed to publish
        this repository (or a direct copy of it)
        over HTTP or FTP.  See <xref linkend="git-update-server-info(1)"/>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--window=[N]
</term>
<term>
--depth=[N]
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        These two options affect how the objects contained in the pack are
        stored using delta compression. The objects are first internally
        sorted by type, size and optionally names and compared against the
        other objects within <literal>--window</literal> to see if using delta compression saves
        space. <literal>--depth</literal> limits the maximum delta depth; making it too deep
        affects the performance on the unpacker side, because delta data needs
        to be applied that many times to get to the necessary object.
        The default value for --window is 10 and --depth is 50.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--window-memory=[N]
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        This option provides an additional limit on top of <literal>--window</literal>;
        the window size will dynamically scale down so as to not take
        up more than N bytes in memory.  This is useful in
        repositories with a mix of large and small objects to not run
        out of memory with a large window, but still be able to take
        advantage of the large window for the smaller objects.  The
        size can be suffixed with "k", "m", or "g".
        <literal>--window-memory=0</literal> makes memory usage unlimited, which is the
        default.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--max-pack-size=&lt;n&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Maximum size of each output packfile, expressed in MiB.
        If specified,  multiple packfiles may be created.
        The default is unlimited.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_configuration">
<title>Configuration</title>
<simpara>When configuration variable <literal>repack.UseDeltaBaseOffset</literal> is set
for the repository, the command passes <literal>--delta-base-offset</literal>
option to <emphasis>git-pack-objects</emphasis>; this typically results in slightly
smaller packs, but the generated packs are incompatible with
versions of git older than (and including) v1.4.3; do not set
the variable in a repository that older version of git needs to
be able to read (this includes repositories from which packs can
be copied out over http or rsync, and people who obtained packs
that way can try to use older git with it).</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_author">
<title>Author</title>
<simpara>Written by Linus Torvalds &lt;<ulink url="mailto:torvalds@osdl.org">torvalds@osdl.org</ulink>&gt;</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_documentation">
<title>Documentation</title>
<simpara>Documentation by Ryan Anderson &lt;<ulink url="mailto:ryan@michonline.com">ryan@michonline.com</ulink>&gt;</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_see_also">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<simpara><xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)"/>
<xref linkend="git-prune-packed(1)"/></simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)"/> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</article>
