<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-maintenance(1)">
    <title>git-maintenance(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-maintenance(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-maintenance - Run tasks to optimize Git repository data</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git maintenance</emphasis> run [&lt;options&gt;]</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Run tasks to optimize Git repository data, speeding up other Git commands
and reducing storage requirements for the repository.</simpara>
<simpara>Git commands that add repository data, such as <emphasis>git add</emphasis> or <emphasis>git fetch</emphasis>,
are optimized for a responsive user experience. These commands do not take
time to optimize the Git data, since such optimizations scale with the full
size of the repository while these user commands each perform a relatively
small action.</simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis>git maintenance</emphasis> command provides flexibility for how to optimize the
Git repository.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__subcommands">
<title>SUBCOMMANDS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
run
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Run one or more maintenance tasks. If one or more <emphasis>--task</emphasis> options
        are specified, then those tasks are run in that order. Otherwise,
        the tasks are determined by which <emphasis>maintenance.&lt;task&gt;.enabled</emphasis>
        config options are true. By default, only <emphasis>maintenance.gc.enabled</emphasis>
        is true.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__tasks">
<title>TASKS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
commit-graph
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The <emphasis>commit-graph</emphasis> job updates the <emphasis>commit-graph</emphasis> files incrementally,
        then verifies that the written data is correct. The incremental
        write is safe to run alongside concurrent Git processes since it
        will not expire <emphasis>.graph</emphasis> files that were in the previous
        <emphasis>commit-graph-chain</emphasis> file. They will be deleted by a later run based
        on the expiration delay.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
gc
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Clean up unnecessary files and optimize the local repository. "GC"
        stands for "garbage collection," but this task performs many
        smaller tasks. This task can be expensive for large repositories,
        as it repacks all Git objects into a single pack-file. It can also
        be disruptive in some situations, as it deletes stale data. See
        <xref linkend="git-gc(1)" /> for more details on garbage collection in Git.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--auto
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        When combined with the <emphasis>run</emphasis> subcommand, run maintenance tasks
        only if certain thresholds are met. For example, the <emphasis>gc</emphasis> task
        runs when the number of loose objects exceeds the number stored
        in the <emphasis>gc.auto</emphasis> config setting, or when the number of pack-files
        exceeds the <emphasis>gc.autoPackLimit</emphasis> config setting.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--quiet
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Do not report progress or other information over <emphasis>stderr</emphasis>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--task=&lt;task&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        If this option is specified one or more times, then only run the
        specified tasks in the specified order. If no <emphasis>--task=&lt;task&gt;</emphasis>
        arguments are specified, then only the tasks with
        <emphasis>maintenance.&lt;task&gt;.enabled</emphasis> configured as <emphasis>true</emphasis> are considered.
        See the <emphasis>TASKS</emphasis> section for the list of accepted <emphasis>&lt;task&gt;</emphasis> values.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-maintenance(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
