<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="git-index-pack(1)">
    <title>git-index-pack(1)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>git-index-pack(1)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>git-index-pack - Build pack index file for an existing packed archive</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<blockquote>
<literallayout><emphasis>git index-pack</emphasis> [-v] [-o &lt;index-file&gt;] &lt;pack-file&gt;
<emphasis>git index-pack</emphasis> --stdin [--fix-thin] [--keep] [-v] [-o &lt;index-file&gt;]
                 [&lt;pack-file&gt;]</literallayout>
</blockquote>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Reads a packed archive (.pack) from the specified file, and
builds a pack index file (.idx) for it.  The packed archive
together with the pack index can then be placed in the
objects/pack/ directory of a Git repository.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-v
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Be verbose about what is going on, including progress status.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-o &lt;index-file&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Write the generated pack index into the specified
        file.  Without this option the name of pack index
        file is constructed from the name of packed archive
        file by replacing .pack with .idx (and the program
        fails if the name of packed archive does not end
        with .pack).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--stdin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        When this flag is provided, the pack is read from stdin
        instead and a copy is then written to &lt;pack-file&gt;. If
        &lt;pack-file&gt; is not specified, the pack is written to
        objects/pack/ directory of the current Git repository with
        a default name determined from the pack content.  If
        &lt;pack-file&gt; is not specified consider using --keep to
        prevent a race condition between this process and
        <emphasis>git repack</emphasis>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--fix-thin
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Fix a "thin" pack produced by <emphasis>git pack-objects --thin</emphasis> (see
        <xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)" /> for details) by adding the
        excluded objects the deltified objects are based on to the
        pack. This option only makes sense in conjunction with --stdin.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--keep
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Before moving the index into its final destination
        create an empty .keep file for the associated pack file.
        This option is usually necessary with --stdin to prevent a
        simultaneous <emphasis>git repack</emphasis> process from deleting
        the newly constructed pack and index before refs can be
        updated to use objects contained in the pack.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--keep=&lt;msg&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Like --keep create a .keep file before moving the index into
        its final destination, but rather than creating an empty file
        place <emphasis>&lt;msg&gt;</emphasis> followed by an LF into the .keep file.  The <emphasis>&lt;msg&gt;</emphasis>
        message can later be searched for within all .keep files to
        locate any which have outlived their usefulness.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--index-version=&lt;version&gt;[,&lt;offset&gt;]
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        This is intended to be used by the test suite only. It allows
        to force the version for the generated pack index, and to force
        64-bit index entries on objects located above the given offset.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--strict
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Die, if the pack contains broken objects or links.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--check-self-contained-and-connected
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Die if the pack contains broken links. For internal use only.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--threads=&lt;n&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Specifies the number of threads to spawn when resolving
        deltas. This requires that index-pack be compiled with
        pthreads otherwise this option is ignored with a warning.
        This is meant to reduce packing time on multiprocessor
        machines. The required amount of memory for the delta search
        window is however multiplied by the number of threads.
        Specifying 0 will cause Git to auto-detect the number of CPU's
        and use maximum 3 threads.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__note">
<title>Note</title>
<simpara>Once the index has been created, the list of object names is sorted
and the SHA-1 hash of that list is printed to stdout. If --stdin was
also used then this is prefixed by either "pack\t", or "keep\t" if a
new .keep file was successfully created. This is useful to remove a
.keep file used as a lock to prevent the race with <emphasis>git repack</emphasis>
mentioned above.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="git-index-pack(1)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
