<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">

<sect2 lang="en" id="gitpacking(7)">
    <title>gitpacking(7)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>gitpacking(7)</primary>
</indexterm>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__name">
<title>NAME</title>
<simpara>gitpacking - Advanced concepts related to packing in Git</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__synopsis">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<simpara>gitpacking</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>This document aims to describe some advanced concepts related to packing
in Git.</simpara>
<simpara>Many concepts are currently described scattered between manual pages of
various Git commands, including <xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)" />,
<xref linkend="git-repack(1)" />, and others, as well as <xref linkend="gitformat-pack(5)" />,
and parts of the <emphasis>Documentation/technical</emphasis> tree.</simpara>
<simpara>There are many aspects of packing in Git that are not covered in this
document that instead live in the aforementioned areas. Over time, those
scattered bits may coalesce into this document.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__pseudo_merge_bitmaps">
<title>Pseudo-merge bitmaps</title>
<note><simpara>Pseudo-merge bitmaps are considered an experimental feature, so
the configuration and many of the ideas are subject to change.</simpara></note>
<section id="gitpacking(7)__background">
<title>Background</title>
<simpara>Reachability bitmaps are most efficient when we have on-disk stored
bitmaps for one or more of the starting points of a traversal. For this
reason, Git prefers storing bitmaps for commits at the tips of refs,
because traversals tend to start with those points.</simpara>
<simpara>But if you have a large number of refs, it's not feasible to store a
bitmap for <emphasis>every</emphasis> ref tip. It takes up space, and just OR-ing all of
those bitmaps together is expensive.</simpara>
<simpara>One way we can deal with that is to create bitmaps that represent
<emphasis>groups</emphasis> of refs. When a traversal asks about the entire group, then we
can use this single bitmap instead of considering each ref individually.
Because these bitmaps represent the set of objects which would be
reachable in a hypothetical merge of all of the commits, we call them
pseudo-merge bitmaps.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="gitpacking(7)__overview">
<title>Overview</title>
<simpara>A "pseudo-merge bitmap" is used to refer to a pair of bitmaps, as
follows:</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Commit bitmap
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  A bitmap whose set bits describe the set of commits included in the
  pseudo-merge's "merge" bitmap (as below).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Merge bitmap
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  A bitmap whose set bits describe the reachability closure over the set
  of commits in the pseudo-merge's "commits" bitmap (as above). An
  identical bitmap would be generated for an octopus merge with the same
  set of parents as described in the commits bitmap.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<simpara>Pseudo-merge bitmaps can accelerate bitmap traversals when all commits
for a given pseudo-merge are listed on either side of the traversal,
either directly (by explicitly asking for them as part of the <emphasis>HAVES</emphasis>
or <emphasis>WANTS</emphasis>) or indirectly (by encountering them during a fill-in
traversal).</simpara>
</section>
<section id="gitpacking(7)__use_cases">
<title>Use-cases</title>
<simpara>For example, suppose there exists a pseudo-merge bitmap with a large
number of commits, all of which are listed in the <emphasis>WANTS</emphasis> section of
some bitmap traversal query. When pseudo-merge bitmaps are enabled, the
bitmap machinery can quickly determine there is a pseudo-merge which
satisfies some subset of the wanted objects on either side of the query.
Then, we can inflate the EWAH-compressed bitmap, and <emphasis>OR</emphasis> it in to the
resulting bitmap. By contrast, without pseudo-merge bitmaps, we would
have to repeat the decompression and <emphasis>OR</emphasis>-ing step over a potentially
large number of individual bitmaps, which can take proportionally more
time.</simpara>
<simpara>Another benefit of pseudo-merges arises when there is some combination
of (a) a large number of references, with (b) poor bitmap coverage, and
(c) deep, nested trees, making fill-in traversal relatively expensive.
For example, suppose that there are a large enough number of tags where
bitmapping each of the tags individually is infeasible. Without
pseudo-merge bitmaps, computing the result of, say, <emphasis>git rev-list
--use-bitmap-index --count --objects --tags</emphasis> would likely require a
large amount of fill-in traversal. But when a large quantity of those
tags are stored together in a pseudo-merge bitmap, the bitmap machinery
can take advantage of the fact that we only care about the union of
objects reachable from all of those tags, and answer the query much
faster.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="gitpacking(7)__configuration">
<title>Configuration</title>
<simpara>Reference tips are grouped into different pseudo-merge groups according
to two criteria. A reference name matches one or more of the defined
pseudo-merge patterns, and optionally one or more capture groups within
that pattern which further partition the group.</simpara>
<simpara>Within a group, commits may be considered "stable", or "unstable"
depending on their age. These are adjusted by setting the
<emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.stableThreshold</emphasis> and
<emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.threshold</emphasis> configuration values, respectively.</simpara>
<simpara>All stable commits are grouped into pseudo-merges of equal size
(<emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.stableSize</emphasis>). If the <emphasis>stableSize</emphasis>
configuration is set to, say, 100, then the first 100 commits (ordered
by committer date) which are older than the <emphasis>stableThreshold</emphasis> value will
form one group, the next 100 commits will form another group, and so on.</simpara>
<simpara>Among unstable commits, the pseudo-merge machinery will attempt to
combine older commits into large groups as opposed to newer commits
which will appear in smaller groups. This is based on the heuristic that
references whose tip commit is older are less likely to be modified to
point at a different commit than a reference whose tip commit is newer.</simpara>
<simpara>The size of groups is determined by a power-law decay function, and the
decay parameter roughly corresponds to "k" in <emphasis>f(n) = C*n^(-k/100)</emphasis>,
where <emphasis>f(n)</emphasis> describes the size of the <emphasis>n</emphasis>-th pseudo-merge group. The
sample rate controls what percentage of eligible commits are considered
as candidates. The threshold parameter indicates the minimum age (so as
to avoid including too-recent commits in a pseudo-merge group, making it
less likely to be valid). The "maxMerges" parameter sets an upper-bound
on the number of pseudo-merge commits an individual group</simpara>
<simpara>The "stable"-related parameters control "stable" pseudo-merge groups,
comprised of a fixed number of commits which are older than the
configured "stable threshold" value and may be grouped together in
chunks of "stableSize" in order of age.</simpara>
<simpara>The exact configuration for pseudo-merges is as follows:</simpara>
<note><simpara>The configuration options in <emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.*</emphasis> are considered
EXPERIMENTAL and may be subject to change or be removed entirely in the
future. For more information about the pseudo-merge bitmap feature, see
the "Pseudo-merge bitmaps" section of <xref linkend="gitpacking(7)" />.</simpara></note>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.pattern
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Regular expression used to match reference names. Commits
        pointed to by references matching this pattern (and meeting
        the below criteria, like <emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.sampleRate</emphasis>
        and <emphasis>bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.threshold</emphasis>) will be considered
        for inclusion in a pseudo-merge bitmap.
</simpara>
<simpara>Commits are grouped into pseudo-merge groups based on whether or not
any reference(s) that point at a given commit match the pattern, which
is an extended regular expression.</simpara>
<simpara>Within a pseudo-merge group, commits may be further grouped into
sub-groups based on the capture groups in the pattern. These
sub-groupings are formed from the regular expressions by concatenating
any capture groups from the regular expression, with a <emphasis>-</emphasis> dash in
between.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, if the pattern is <emphasis>refs/tags/</emphasis>, then all tags (provided
they meet the below criteria) will be considered candidates for the
same pseudo-merge group. However, if the pattern is instead
<emphasis>refs/remotes/([0-9])+/tags/</emphasis>, then tags from different remotes will
be grouped into separate pseudo-merge groups, based on the remote
number.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.decay
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the rate at which consecutive pseudo-merge bitmap
        groups decrease in size. Must be non-negative. This parameter
        can be thought of as <emphasis>k</emphasis> in the function <emphasis>f(n) = C * n^-k</emphasis>,
        where <emphasis>f(n)</emphasis> is the size of the `n`th group.
</simpara>
<simpara>Setting the decay rate equal to <emphasis>0</emphasis> will cause all groups to be the
same size. Setting the decay rate equal to <emphasis>1</emphasis> will cause the <emphasis>n`th
group to be `1/n</emphasis> the size of the initial group.  Higher values of the
decay rate cause consecutive groups to shrink at an increasing rate.
The default is <emphasis>1</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>If all groups are the same size, it is possible that groups containing
newer commits will be able to be used less often than earlier groups,
since it is more likely that the references pointing at newer commits
will be updated more often than a reference pointing at an old commit.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.sampleRate
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the proportion of non-bitmapped commits (among
        reference tips) which are selected for inclusion in an
        unstable pseudo-merge bitmap. Must be between <emphasis>0</emphasis> and <emphasis>1</emphasis>
        (inclusive). The default is <emphasis>1</emphasis>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.threshold
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the minimum age of non-bitmapped commits (among
        reference tips, as above) which are candidates for inclusion
        in an unstable pseudo-merge bitmap. The default is
        <emphasis>1.week.ago</emphasis>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.maxMerges
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the maximum number of pseudo-merge commits among
        which commits may be distributed.
</simpara>
<simpara>For pseudo-merge groups whose pattern does not contain any capture
groups, this setting is applied for all commits matching the regular
expression. For patterns that have one or more capture groups, this
setting is applied for each distinct capture group.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, if your capture group is <emphasis>refs/tags/</emphasis>, then this setting
will distribute all tags into a maximum of <emphasis>maxMerges</emphasis> pseudo-merge
commits. However, if your capture group is, say,
<emphasis>refs/remotes/([0-9]+)/tags/</emphasis>, then this setting will be applied to
each remote's set of tags individually.</simpara>
<simpara>Must be non-negative. The default value is 64.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.stableThreshold
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the minimum age of commits (among reference tips,
        as above, however stable commits are still considered
        candidates even when they have been covered by a bitmap) which
        are candidates for a stable a pseudo-merge bitmap. The default
        is <emphasis>1.month.ago</emphasis>.
</simpara>
<simpara>Setting this threshold to a smaller value (e.g., 1.week.ago) will cause
more stable groups to be generated (which impose a one-time generation
cost) but those groups will likely become stale over time. Using a
larger value incurs the opposite penalty (fewer stable groups which are
more useful).</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
bitmapPseudoMerge.&lt;name&gt;.stableSize
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Determines the size (in number of commits) of a stable
        psuedo-merge bitmap. The default is <emphasis>512</emphasis>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section id="gitpacking(7)__examples">
<title>Examples</title>
<simpara>Suppose that you have a repository with a large number of references,
and you want a bare-bones configuration of pseudo-merge bitmaps that
will enhance bitmap coverage of the <emphasis>refs/</emphasis> namespace. You may start
with a configuration like so:</simpara>
<screen>[bitmapPseudoMerge "all"]
        pattern = "refs/"
        threshold = now
        stableThreshold = never
        sampleRate = 100
        maxMerges = 64</screen>
<simpara>This will create pseudo-merge bitmaps for all references, regardless of
their age, and group them into 64 pseudo-merge commits.</simpara>
<simpara>If you wanted to separate tags from branches when generating
pseudo-merge commits, you would instead define the pattern with a
capture group, like so:</simpara>
<screen>[bitmapPseudoMerge "all"]
        pattern = "refs/(heads/tags)/"</screen>
<simpara>Suppose instead that you are working in a fork-network repository, with
each fork specified by some numeric ID, and whose refs reside in
<emphasis>refs/virtual/NNN/</emphasis> (where <emphasis>NNN</emphasis> is the numeric ID corresponding to some
fork) in the network. In this instance, you may instead write something
like:</simpara>
<screen>[bitmapPseudoMerge "all"]
        pattern = "refs/virtual/([0-9]+)/(heads|tags)/"
        threshold = now
        stableThreshold = never
        sampleRate = 100
        maxMerges = 64</screen>
<simpara>Which would generate pseudo-merge group identifiers like "1234-heads",
and "5678-tags" (for branches in fork "1234", and tags in remote "5678",
respectively).</simpara>
</section>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__see_also">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<simpara><xref linkend="git-pack-objects(1)" />
<xref linkend="git-repack(1)" /></simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="gitpacking(7)__git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <xref linkend="git(1)" /> suite</simpara>
</simplesect>
</sect2>
