<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry">
	<title>Registry Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>registry</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		A few infrequently used settings are available only by editing
		the registry directly. It goes without saying that you should
		only edit registry values if you know what you are doing.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Configuration</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You can specify a different location for the Git
					configuration file using registry location
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\ConfigDir</literal>.
					This will affect all TortoiseGit operations.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Cache tray icon</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					To add a cache tray icon for the TSVNCache program,
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\CacheTrayIcon</literal>.
					This is really only useful for developers as it allows
					you to terminate the program gracefully.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Debug</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					To show the command line parameters passed from the shell
					extension to TortoiseProc.exe
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\Debug</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Owner-Drawn Menus</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This can be useful if you use something other than the windows explorer
					or if you get problems with the context menu displaying correctly.
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> key with a value of 0 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\OwnerdrawnMenus</literal>
					if you don't want TortoiseGit to use owner-draw menu items in the shell
					context menu. Set this value to 2 if you don't want TortoiseGit to use
					icons in the context menu at all.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Block Overlay Status</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you don't want the explorer to update the status overlays while another
					TortoiseGit command is running (e.g. Update, Commit, ...) then
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\BlockStatus</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Update Check URL</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\UpdateCheckURL</literal>
					contains the URL from which TortoiseGit tries to download a text file
					to find out if there are updates available. You can also set this under
					<literal>HKLM</literal> instead of <literal>HKCU</literal> if you want,
					but <literal>HKCU</literal> overwrites the setting in <literal>HKLM</literal>.
					This might be useful for company admins who don't want their users to
					update TortoiseGit until they approve it.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Filenames without extensions in auto-completion list</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The auto-completion list shown in the commit message editor
					displays the names of files listed for commit.
					To also include these names with extensions removed,
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\AutocompleteRemovesExtensions</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Explorer columns everywhere</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The extra columns the TortoiseGit adds to the details view
					in Windows Explorer are normally only active in a working
					copy. If you want those to be accessible everywhere, not
					just in working copies, create a <literal>DWORD</literal>
					key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\ColumnsEveryWhere</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Merge log separator</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When you merge revisions from another branch, and merge tracking
					information is available, the log messages from the revisions
					you merge will be collected to make up a commit log message.
					A pre-defined string is used to separate the individual log
					messages of the merged revisions. If you prefer, you can create
					a <literal>SZ</literal> key at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\MergeLogSeparator</literal>
					containing a separator string of your choice.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Always blame changes with TortoiseMerge</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseGit allows you to assign external diff viewer.
					Most such viewers, however, are not suited for change blaming
					(<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-blame-diffs"/>),
					so you might wish to fall back to TortoiseMerge in this case.
					To do so, create a <literal>DWORD</literal>	key with a value of 1 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\DiffBlamesWithTortoiseMerge</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Current revision highlighting for folders in log dialog</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The log dialog highlights the current working copy revision
					when the log is shown for a file. To do the same thing for a
					folder requires a working copy crawl, which can be a slow
					operation for large working copies.
					If you want to enable this feature you must create a
					<literal>DWORD</literal> registry key at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\RecursiveLogRev</literal>.
					A value of 0 disables the feature (no highlighting for folders),
					a value of 1 (default) will fetch the status recursively (find the
					highest revision in the working copy tree), and a value of 2 will
					check the revision of the selected folder itself, but will
					not check any child items.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Make checkout fail if an item of the same name exists</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					By default, if you checkout a working copy over an existing
					unversioned folder structure, as you might do after import,
					then any existing which differ from the repository content
					will be left unchanged and marked as modified. When you come
					to commit, it is your local copy which will then be sent back
					to the repository. Some people would prefer the checkout to
					fail if the existing content differs, so that if two people
					add the same file the second person's version does not
					overwrite the original version by mistake.
					If you want to force checkouts to fail in this instance you must
					create a <literal>DWORD</literal> registry key with value 0 at
					<literal>HKCU\Software\TortoiseGit\AllowUnversionedObstruction</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</sect2>
