<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry">
    <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGS_CONFIG"?>
    <title>Advanced Settings</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>registry</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
        A few infrequently used settings are available only in the advanced
        page of the settings dialog. These settings modify the registry directly
        and you have to know what each of these settings is used for and what
        it does. Do not modify these settings unless you are sure you need to
        change them.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">AutocompleteRemovesExtensions</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The auto-completion list shown in the commit message editor
                    displays the names of files listed for commit.
                    To also include these names with extensions removed,
                    set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">BlockStatus</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    If you don't want the explorer to update the status overlays
                    while another TortoiseGit command is running
                    (e.g. Update, Commit, ...) then set this value to
                    <literal>true</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">CacheTrayIcon</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    To add a cache tray icon for the TSVNCache program, set
                    this value to <literal>true</literal>.
                    This is really only useful for developers as it allows
                    you to terminate the program gracefully.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">ColumnsEveryWhere</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The extra columns the TortoiseGit adds to the details view
                    in Windows Explorer are normally only active in a working
                    copy. If you want those to be accessible everywhere, not
                    just in working copies, set this value to
                    <literal>true</literal>.
                    Note that the extra columns are only available in XP.
                    Vista and later doesn't support that feature any more.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">Debug</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Set this to <literal>true</literal> if you want a dialog to
                    pop up for every command showing the command line used to
                    start TortoiseProc.exe.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">DiffBlamesWithTortoiseMerge</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    TortoiseGit allows you to assign an external diff viewer.
                    Most such viewers, however, are not suited for change blaming
                    (<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-blame-diffs"/>),
                    so you might wish to fall back to TortoiseMerge in this case.
                    To do so, set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">FullRowSelect</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The status list control which is used in various dialogs
                    (e.g., commit, check-for-modifications, add, revert, ...)
                    uses full row selection (i.e., if you select an entry, the
                    full row is selected, not just the first column).
                    This is fine, but the selected row then also covers the
                    background image on the bottom right, which can look ugly.
                    To disable full row select, set this value to
                    <literal>false</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">ShowContextMenuIcons</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    This can be useful if you use something other than the windows explorer
                    or if you get problems with the context menu displaying incorrectly.
                    Set this value to <literal>false</literal>
                    if you don't want TortoiseGit to show icons for the
                    shell context menu items.
                    Set this value to <literal>true</literal> to show the icons again.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">UseLibgit2</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    This makes TortoiseGit to use libgit2 as much as possible (e.g. for
                    adding files to the index). It's disabled by default, since libgit2
                    has some limitations ATM (UTF8 filename problems, doesn't support AutoCRLF and separate-git-dir).
                    If you t want TortoiseGit to use libgit2, set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">VersionCheck</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    TortoiseGit checks whether there's a new version available
                    about once a week. If you don't want TortoiseGit to do this
                    check, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
</sect2>
