<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage">
	<title>Project Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>properties</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-1">
			<title>Explorer property page, Git tab</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/Properties.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you want to have more detailed information
		about a file/directory than just the icon overlay.
		You can get all the information Git provides in the
		explorer properties dialog. Just select the file or
		directory and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Windows Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		in the context menu (note: this is the normal properties menu entry
		the explorer provides, not the one in the TortoiseGit submenu!).
		In the properties dialog box TortoiseGit has added a new
		property page for files/folders under Git control,
		where you can see all relevant information about the
		selected file/directory.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props">
		<title>Git Properties</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Git properties</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTIES"?>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTYVALUE"?>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-2">
				<title>Git property page</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/PropertyList.png"/>
			</figure>
			You can read and set the Git properties
			from the Windows properties dialog, but also from
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			and within TortoiseGit's status lists, from
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can add your own properties, or some properties with a 
			special meaning in Git. These begin with <literal>svn:</literal>. 
			<literal>svn:externals</literal> is such a property; see how to handle
			externals in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-import-4"/>.
		</para>
		<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-keywords">
			<title>svn:keywords</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>keywords</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>expand keywords</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				Git supports CVS-like keyword expansion which can be
				used to embed filename and revision information within the
				file itself. Keywords currently supported are:
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">$Date$</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Date of last known commit. This is based on
								information obtained when you update your working
								copy. It does <emphasis>not</emphasis> check the
								repository to find more recent changes.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">$Revision$</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Revision of last known commit.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">$Author$</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Author who made the last known commit.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">$HeadURL$</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								The full URL of this file in the repository.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">$Id$</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								A compressed combination of the previous
								four keywords.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
				To find out how to use these keywords, look at the
				<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.props.special.keywords.html">
					<citetitle>svn:keywords section</citetitle>
				</ulink>
				in the Git book, which gives a full description of these
				keywords and how to enable and use them.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<para>
			For more information about properties in Git see the 
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.props.html">
				<citetitle>Special Properties</citetitle>
			</ulink>.
		</para>
		<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-add">
			<title>Adding and Editing Properties</title>
			<para>
				<figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-add">
					<title>Adding properties</title>
					<graphic fileref="../images/PropertyAdd.png"/>
				</figure>
				To add a new property, first click on <guilabel>Add...</guilabel>.
				Select the required property name from the combo box,
				or type in a name of your own choice, then enter a value
				in the box below. Properties which take multiple values, such as an
				ignore list, can be entered on multiple lines.
				Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to add that property to the list.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you want to apply a property to many items at once, select the
				files/folders in explorer, then select
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
			</para>
			<para>
				If you want to apply the property to <emphasis>every</emphasis> file
				and folder in the hierarchy below the current folder, check the
				<guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox.
			</para>
			<para>
				Some properties, for example <literal>svn:needs-lock</literal>,
				can only be applied to files, so the property name doesn't appear
				in the drop down list for folders. You can still apply such a
				property recursively to all files in a hierarchy, but you have
				to type in the property name yourself.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you wish to edit an existing property, select that property from
				the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you wish to remove an existing property, select that property from
				the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>svn:externals</literal> property can be used to
				pull in other projects from the same repository or a completely
				different repository. For more information, read
				<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-import-4"/>.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-import">
			<title>Exporting and Importing Properties</title>
			<para>
				Often you will find yourself applying the same set of properties many
				times, for example <literal>bugtraq:logregex</literal>. To simplify
				the process of copying properties from one project to another, you
				can use the Export/Import feature.
			</para>
			<para>
				From the file or folder where the properties are already set, use
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>,
				select the properties you wish to export and click on
				<guibutton>Export...</guibutton>. You will be prompted for a filename
				where the property names and values will be saved.
			</para>
			<para>
				From the folder(s) where you wish to apply these properties, use
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
				and click on <guibutton>Import...</guibutton>. You will be prompted
				for a filename to import from, so navigate to the place you saved
				the export file previously and select it. The properties will be added
				to the folders non-recursively.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you want to add properties to a tree recursively, follow the steps
				above, then in the property dialog select each property in turn,
				click on <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>, check the
				<guilabel>Apply property recursively</guilabel> box and click on
				<guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The Import file format is binary and proprietary to TortoiseGit.
				Its only purpose is to transfer properties using Import and Export,
				so there is no need to edit these files.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-binary">
			<title>Binary Properties</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseGit can handle binary property values using files.
				To read a binary property value, <guibutton>Save...</guibutton>
				to a file. To set a binary value, use a hex editor or other appropriate
				tool to create a file with the content you require, then
				<guibutton>Load...</guibutton> from that file.
			</para>
			<para>
				Although binary properties are not often used, they can be useful in
				some applications. For example if you are storing huge graphics files,
				or if the application used to load the file is huge, you might want
				to store a thumbnail as a property so you can obtain a preview quickly.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-auto-props">
			<title>Automatic property setting</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>auto-props</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				You can configure Git and TortoiseGit to set properties
				automatically on files and folders when they are added to the
				repository. There are two ways of doing this.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can edit the Git configuration file to enable
				this feature on your client. The <guilabel>General</guilabel>
				page of TortoiseGit's settings dialog has an edit button to
				take you there directly.
				The config file is a simple text file which controls some of
				Git's workings. You need to change two things:
				firstly in the section headed
				<literal>miscellany</literal> uncomment the line
				<literal>enable-auto-props = yes</literal>.
				Secondly you need to edit the section below to define which
				properties you want added to which file types.
				This method is a standard Git feature and works with
				any Git client. However it has to be defined on each
				client individually - there is no way to propagate these settings
				from the repository.
			</para>
			<para>
				An alternative method is to set the <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal>
				property on folders, as described in the next section. This method
				only works for TortoiseGit clients, but it does get propagated
				to all working trees on update.
			</para>
			<para>
				Whichever method you choose, you should note that auto-props
				are only applied to files at the time they are added to the
				repository. Auto-props will never change the properties of files
				which are already versioned.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you want to be absolutely sure that new files have the correct
				properties applied, you should set up a repository pre-commit
				hook to reject commits where the required properties are not set.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<important>
			<title>Commit properties</title>
			<para>
				Git properties are versioned. After you change or add a 
				property you have to commit your changes.
			</para>
		</important>
		<tip>
			<title>Conflicts on properties</title>
			<para>
				If there's a conflict on committing the changes, because another 
				user has changed the same property, Git generates a 
				<filename>.prej</filename> file. Delete this file after you 
				have resolved the conflict.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props">
		<title>TortoiseGit Project Properties</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>project properties</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>TortoiseGit properties</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			TortoiseGit has a few special properties of its own, and these begin
			with <literal>tsvn:</literal>.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>
						sets the minimum length of a log message for a commit.
						If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the commit
						is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
						supply a proper descriptive message for every commit.
						If this property is not set,
						or the value is zero, empty log messages are allowed.
					</para>
					<para>
						<literal>tsvn:lockmsgminsize</literal>
						sets the minimum length of a lock message.
						If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the lock
						is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
						supply a proper descriptive message for every lock you get.
						If this property is not set,
						or the value is zero, empty lock messages are allowed.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<literal>tsvn:logwidthmarker</literal> is used with projects which
						require log messages to be formatted with some maximum width
						(typically 80 characters) before a line break. Setting this
						property to a non-zero will do 2 things in the log message
						entry dialog: it places a marker to indicate the maximum width,
						and it disables word wrap in the display, so that you can see
						whether the text you entered is too long. Note: this feature
						will only work correctly if you have a fixed-width font
						selected for log messages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal> is used with projects which
						have rules about log message formatting. The property holds
						a multi-line text string which will be inserted in the commit
						message box when you start a commit. You can then edit it to
						include the required information. Note: if you are also using
						<literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>, be sure to set the length
						longer than the template or you will lose the protection mechanism.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Git allows you to set <quote>autoprops</quote> which
						will be applied to newly added or imported files, based on
						the file extension. This depends on every client having set
						appropriate autoprops in their Git configuration file.
						<literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal> can be set on folders
						and these will be merged with the user's local autoprops
						when importing or adding files.
						The format is the same as for Git autoprops, e.g.
						<literal>*.sh = svn:eol-style=native;svn:executable</literal>
						sets two properties on files with the <literal>.sh</literal>
						extension.
					</para>
					<para>
						If there is a conflict between the local autoprops and
						<literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal>, the project settings take
						precedence because they are specific to that project.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the Commit dialog you have the option to paste in the
						list of changed files, including the status of each file
						(added, modified, etc).
						<literal>tsvn:logfilelistenglish</literal> defines whether
						the file status is inserted in English or in the localized
						language. If the property is not set, the default is
						<literal>true</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						TortoiseGit can use spell checker modules which are also
						used by OpenOffice and Mozilla. If you have those installed
						this property will determine which spell checker to use, i.e.
						in which language the log messages for your project should
						be written.
						<literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> sets the language
						module the spell checking engine should use when you enter
						a log message. You can find the values for your language
						on this page:
						<ulink url="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms776260.aspx">
							<citetitle>MSDN: Language Identifiers</citetitle>
						</ulink>.
					</para>
					<para>
						You can enter this value in decimal, or in hexadecimal if
						prefixed with <literal>0x</literal>.
						For example English (US) can be entered as
						<literal>0x0409</literal> or <literal>1033</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The property <literal>tsvn:logsummary</literal> is used to
						extract a portion of the log message which is then shown
						in the log dialog as the log message summary.
					</para>
					<para>
						The value of the <literal>tsvn:logsummary</literal> property
						must be set to a one line regex string which contains one
						regex group. Whatever matches that group is used as the
						summary.
					</para>
					<para>
						An example: 
						<literal>\[SUMMARY\]:\s+(.*)</literal> 
						Will catch everything after <quote>[SUMMARY]</quote> in the log message
						and use that as the summary.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you want to add a new property, you can either pick one from
						the list in the combo box, or you can enter any property name
						you like. If your project uses some custom properties,
						and you want those properties to appear in the list in the combo
						box (to avoid typos when you enter a property name), you can
						create a list of your custom properties using
						<literal>tsvn:userfileproperties</literal> and
						<literal>tsvn:userdirproperties</literal>.
						Apply these properties to a folder. When you go to edit
						the properties of any child item, your custom properties will
						appear in the list of pre-defined property names.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Some <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties require a
			<literal>true/false</literal> value. TortoiseGit also understands
			<literal>yes</literal> as a synonym for <literal>true</literal> and
			<literal>no</literal> as a synonym for <literal>false</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			TortoiseGit can integrate with some bug tracking tools. This uses
			project properties that start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-bugtracker"/> for further information.
		</para>
		<para>
			It can also integrate with some web-based repository browsers,
			using project properties that start with <literal>webviewer:</literal>.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-repoviewer"/> for further information.
		</para>
		<important>
			<title>Set the project properties on folders</title>
			<para>
				These special project properties must be set on
				<emphasis>folders</emphasis> for the system to work. 
				When you commit a file or folder the properties are read from that folder.
				If the properties are not found there, TortoiseGit will search upwards
				through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
				folder, or the tree root (eg. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
				If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
				<filename>trunk/</filename> and not some sub-folder, then it is
				sufficient to set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
				If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively on each sub-folder.
				A property setting deeper in the project hierarchy overrides settings on
				higher levels (closer to <filename>trunk/</filename>).
			</para>
			<para>
				For project properties <emphasis>only</emphasis>
				you can use the <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox to set
				the property to all sub-folders in the hierarchy, without also
				setting it on all files.
			</para>
		</important>
		<para>
			When you add new sub-folders using TortoiseGit, any
			project properties present in the parent folder
			will automatically be added to the new child folder too.
		</para>
		<caution>
			<para>
				Although TortoiseGit's project properties are extremely useful,
				they only work with TortoiseGit, and some will only work in newer versions
				of TortoiseGit. If people working on your project use a variety of
				Git clients, or possibly have old versions of TortoiseGit,
				you may want to use repository hooks to enforce project policies.
				project properties can only help to implement a
				policy, they cannot enforce it.
			</para>
		</caution>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
