<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-export">
	<title>Exporting a Git Working Copy</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>export</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>unversioned 'working copy'</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		Sometimes you may want a copy of your working tree without any of
		those <filename>.svn</filename> directories, e.g. to create a zipped
		tarball of your source, or to export to a web server. Instead of
		making a copy and then deleting all those <filename>.svn</filename>
		directories manually, TortoiseGit offers the command
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Export...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		Exporting from a URL and exporting from a working copy are treated
		slightly differently.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-export-dia-1">
			<title>The Export-from-URL Dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/ExportURL.png"/>
		</figure>
		If you execute this command on an unversioned folder, TortoiseGit will
		assume that the selected folder is the target, and open a dialog for
		you to enter the URL and revision to export from.
		This dialog has options to export only the top level folder, to omit
		external references, and to override the line end style for files which
		have the <literal>svn:eol-style</literal> property set.
	</para>
	<para>
		Of course you can export directly from the repository too.
		Use the Repository Browser to navigate to the relevant subtree
		in your repository, then use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		You will get the <guilabel>Export from URL</guilabel> dialog described above.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you execute this command on your working copy you'll be asked for
		a place to save the <emphasis>clean</emphasis> working copy without the
		<filename>.svn</filename> folders.
		By default, only the versioned files are exported, but you can use the
		<guilabel>Export unversioned files too</guilabel> checkbox to include any other
		unversioned files which exist in your WC and not in the repository.
		External references using <literal>svn:externals</literal> can be
		omitted if required.
	</para>
	<para>
		Another way to export from a working copy is to <action>right drag</action>
		the working copy folder to another location and choose
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>SVN Export here</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		or 
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>SVN Export all here</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		The second option includes the unversioned files as well.
	</para>
	<para>
		When exporting from a working copy,
		if the target folder already contains a folder of the same
		name as the one you are exporting, you will be given the option
		to overwrite the existing content, or to create a new folder with
		an automatically generated name, eg. <literal>Target (1)</literal>.
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Exporting single files</title>
		<para>
			The export dialog does not allow exporting single files, even 
			though Git can.
		</para>
		<para>
			To export single files with TortoiseGit, you have to use
			the repository browser (<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-repobrowser"/>).
			Simply drag the file(s) you want to export from the repository
			browser to where you want them in the explorer, or use the
			context menu in the repository browser to export the files.
		</para>
	</tip>
	<tip>
		<title>Exporting a Change Tree</title>
		<para>
			If you want to export a copy of your project tree structure
			but containing only the files which have changed in a particular
			revision, or between any two revisions, use the compare revisions
			feature described in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-compare-revs"/>.
		</para>
	</tip>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-export-unversion">
		<title>Removing a working copy from version control</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>unversion</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Sometimes you have a working copy which you want to convert back
			to a normal folder without the <literal>.svn</literal> directories.
			What you really need is an export-in-place command, that just
			removes the control directories rather than generating a new
			clean directory tree.
		</para>
		<para>
			The answer is surprisingly simple - export the folder to itself!
			TortoiseGit detects this special case and asks if you want to
			make the working copy unversioned. If you answer
			<emphasis>yes</emphasis> the control directories will be removed
			and you will have a plain, unversioned directory tree.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
