<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tgit-dug-settings-saved-data">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSSAVEDDATA"?>
	<title>Saved Data Settings</title>
	<para>
		<figure id="tgit-dug-settings-dia-saved-data">
			<title>The Settings Dialog, Saved Data Page</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsSavedData.png"/>
		</figure>
		For your convenience, TortoiseGit saves many of the settings
		you use, and remembers where you have been lately. If you
		want to clear out that cache of data, you can do it here.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>URL history</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Whenever you checkout a working tree, merge changes
					or use the repository browser, TortoiseGit keeps a record
					of recently used URLs and offers them in a combo box.
					Sometimes that list gets cluttered with outdated URLs
					so it is useful to flush it out periodically.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to remove a single item from one of the combo
					boxes you can do that in-place. Just click on the arrow
					to drop the combo box down, move the mouse over the item
					you want to remove and type <keycap>Shift+Del</keycap>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Log messages (Input dialog)</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseGit stores recent commit log messages that you
					enter. These are stored per repository, so if you access many
					repositories this list can grow quite large.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Log messages (Show log dialog)</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseGit caches log messages fetched by the Show Log
					dialog to save time when you next show the log. If someone
					else edits a log message and you already have that message
					cached, you will not see the change until you clear the
					cache. Log message caching is enabled on the
					<guilabel>Log Cache</guilabel> tab.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Dialog sizes and positions</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Many dialogs remember the size and screen position that you
					last used.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
<!--
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Authentication data</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When you authenticate with a Git server, the username
					and password are cached locally so you don't have to keep
					entering them. You may want to clear this for security reasons,
					or because you want to access the repository under a different
					username ... does John know you are using his PC?
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to clear authentication data for one particular server only,
					read <xref linkend="tgit-dug-general-auth"/> for instructions
					on how to find the cached data.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
-->
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Action log</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseGit keeps a log of everything written to its progress
					dialogs. This can be useful when, for example, you want to check
					what happened in a recent update command.
				</para>
				<para>
					The log file is limited in length and when it grows too big the
					oldest content is discarded. By default 4000 lines are kept, but
					you can customize that number.
				</para>
				<para>
					From here you can view the log file content, and also clear it.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</sect2>
