<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSBUGTRAQ_CONFIG"?>
	<title>Integration with Bug Tracking Systems / Issue Trackers</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bug tracking</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bug tracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>issue tracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bugtracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		It is very common in Software Development for changes to be related to a specific
		bug or issue ID. Users of bug tracking systems (issue trackers) would like to associate
		the changes they make in Git with a specific ID in their issue tracker.
		Most issue trackers therefore provide a pre-commit hook script which parses the log
		message to find the bug ID with which the commit is associated.
		This is somewhat error prone since it relies on the user to write the log message
		properly so that the pre-commit hook script can parse it correctly.
	</para>
	<para>
		TortoiseGit can help the user in two ways:
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When the user enters a log message, a well defined line including
					the issue number associated with the commit can be added automatically.
					This reduces the risk that the user enters the issue number in a way
					the bug tracking tools can't parse correctly.
				</para>
				<para>
					Or TortoiseGit can highlight the part of
					the entered log message which is recognized by the issue tracker.
					That way the user knows that the log message can be parsed correctly.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When the user browses the log messages, TortoiseGit
					creates a link out of each bug ID in the log message which fires
					up the browser to the issue mentioned.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-link">
		<title>Adding Issue Numbers to Log Messages</title>
		<para>
			You can integrate a bug tracking tool of your choice in
			TortoiseGit. To do this, you have to define
			some configuration, which start with <literal>bugtraq.</literal>.
			These settings can be edited using TortoiseGit settings dialog: <xref linkend="tgit-dug-settings-hooks-issuetracker-config"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			There are two ways to integrate TortoiseGit with issue trackers. One is
			based on simple strings, the other is based on
			<emphasis>regular expressions</emphasis>.
			The configuration used by both approaches are:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term condition="pot">bugtraq.url</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Set this configuration to the URL of your bug tracking tool.
							It must be properly URI encoded and it has to contain
							<literal>%BUGID%</literal>.
							<literal>%BUGID%</literal> is replaced with the Issue number
							you entered. This allows TortoiseGit
							to display a link in the log dialog, so when you are looking
							at the revision log you can jump directly to your
							bug tracking tool.
							You do not have to provide this configuration, but then
							TortoiseGit shows only the
							issue number and not the link to it.
							e.g the TortoiseGit project is using
							<systemitem class="url">https://tortoisegit.org/issue/%BUGID%</systemitem>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term condition="pot">bugtraq.warnifnoissue</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Set this to <literal>true</literal>, if you want
							TortoiseGit to warn you
							because of an empty issue-number text field. Valid values
							are <literal>true/false</literal>.
							<emphasis>
								If not defined, <literal>false</literal> is assumed.
							</emphasis>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
		<sect3 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-link-simple">
			<title>Issue Number in Text Box</title>
			<para>
				In the simple approach, TortoiseGit shows the user a separate
				input field where a bug ID can be entered. Then a separate line
				is appended/prepended to the log message the user entered.
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.message</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This configuration activates the bug tracking system
								in <emphasis>Input field</emphasis> mode.
								If this configuration is set, then TortoiseGit
								will prompt you to enter an issue number when you commit
								your changes. It's used to add a line at the end of the
								log message. It must contain
								<literal>%BUGID%</literal>, which is replaced with the
								issue number on commit. This ensures that your commit log
								contains a reference to the issue number which is always
								in a consistent format and can be parsed by your
								bug tracking tool to associate the issue number with a
								particular commit. As an example you might use
								<literal>Issue : %BUGID%</literal>,
								but this depends on your Tool.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.append</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This configuration defines if the bug-ID is appended (true)
								to the end of the log message or inserted (false) at the
								start of the log message. Valid values are
								<literal>true/false</literal>.
								<emphasis>
									If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed,
									so that existing projects don't break.
								</emphasis>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.label</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This text is shown by TortoiseGit
								on the commit dialog to label the edit box where you enter
								the issue number. If it's not set,
								<literal>Bug-ID / Issue-Nr:</literal> will be displayed.
								Keep in mind though that the window will not be resized
								to fit this label, so keep the size of the label below
								20-25 characters.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.number</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								If set to <literal>true</literal> only numbers are allowed
								in the issue-number text field.
								An exception is the comma, so you can comma separate several
								numbers. Valid values are <literal>true/false</literal>.
								<emphasis>
									If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed.
								</emphasis>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-link-regex">
			<title>Issue Numbers Using Regular Expressions</title>
			<para>
				In the approach with <emphasis>regular expressions</emphasis>, TortoiseGit
				doesn't show a separate input field but marks the part of the log message
				the user enters which is recognized by the issue tracker. This is done while
				the user writes the log message. This also means that the bug ID can be
				anywhere inside a log message! This method is much more flexible, and is
				the one used by the TortoiseGit project itself.
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.logregex</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This configuration activates the bug tracking system
								in <emphasis>Regex</emphasis> mode.
								It contains either a single regular expressions,
								or two regular expressions separated by a newline.
							</para>
							<para>
								If two expressions are set, then the first expression is used as
								a pre-filter to find expressions which contain bug IDs. The
								second expression then extracts the bare bug IDs from the
								result of the first regex. This allows you to use a list
								of bug IDs and natural language expressions if you wish.
								e.g. you might fix several bugs and include a string something
								like this:
								<quote>This change resolves issues #23, #24 and #25</quote>
							</para>
							<para>
								If you want to catch bug IDs as used in the expression above
								inside a log message, you could use the following regex strings,
								which are the ones used by the TortoiseGit project:
								<literal>[Ii]ssues?:?(\s*(,|and)?\s*#\d+)+</literal> and
								<literal>(\d+)</literal>
							</para>
							<para>
								The first expression picks out <quote>issues #23, #24 and #25</quote>
								from the surrounding log message.
								The second regex extracts plain decimal numbers from the output
								of the first regex, so it will return <quote>23</quote>, <quote>24</quote>
								and <quote>25</quote> to use as bug IDs.
							</para>
							<para>
								Breaking the first regex down a little, it must start with
								the word <quote>issue</quote>, possibly capitalised.
								This is optionally followed by an <quote>s</quote> (more than one
								issue) and optionally a colon. This is followed by one or more
								groups each having zero or more leading whitespace, an optional
								comma or <quote>and</quote> and more optional space. Finally there
								is a mandatory <quote>#</quote> and a mandatory decimal number.
							</para>
							<para>
								If only one expression is set, then the bare bug IDs must be
								matched in the groups of the regex string. Example:
								<literal>[Ii]ssue(?:s)? #?(\d+)</literal>
								This method is required by a few issue trackers, e.g. trac,
								but it is harder to construct the regex. We recommend that you
								only use this method if your issue tracker documentation
								tells you to.
							</para>
							<para>
								If you are unfamiliar with regular expressions, take a look at
								the introduction at
								<ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expression">
									<citetitle>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expression</citetitle>
								</ulink>,
								and the online documentation and tutorial at
								<ulink url="http://www.regular-expressions.info/">
									<citetitle>http://www.regular-expressions.info/</citetitle>
								</ulink>.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<para>
			If both the <literal>bugtraq:message</literal> and <literal>bugtraq:logregex</literal>
			properties are set, <literal>logregex</literal> takes precedence.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Even if you don't have an issue tracker with a pre-commit hook parsing your
				log messages, you still can use this to turn the issues mentioned in your
				log messages into links!
			</para>
			<para>
				And even if you don't need the links, the issue numbers show up as a
				separate column in the log dialog, making it easier to find the changes
				which relate to a particular issue.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<sect3 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-link-provider">
			<title>Issue Tracker Provider Settings based on Hierarchical Git Configuration</title>
			<para>
				This is a hierarchical git configuration to associate issue tracker plugin with your project,
				rather than with to a specific directory path. Such settings are more portable.
				To deploy the settings, set to Project level and commit <literal>.tgitconfig</literal>.
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.provideruuid</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This is the GUID of 32-bit issue tracker plugin.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.provideruuid64</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This is the GUID of 64-bit issue tracker plugin.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term condition="pot">bugtraq.providerparams</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								This is the parameter string for the issue tracker plugin.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<para>
			This issue tracker integration is not restricted to TortoiseGit; it can be used
			with other clients (e.g. TortoiseSVN). For more information, read the full
			<ulink url="https://gitlab.com/tortoisegit/tortoisegit/blob/master/doc/issuetrackers.txt">
				<citetitle>Issue Tracker Integration Specification</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			in the TortoiseGit source repository.
			(<xref linkend="tgit-preface-source"/> explains how to access the repository).
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-ref">
		<title>Getting Information from the Issue Tracker</title>
		<para>
			The previous section deals with adding issue information to the
			log messages. But what if you need to get information from the issue
			tracker? The commit dialog has a Windows COM interface which allows
			integration an external program that can talk to your tracker.
			Typically you might want to query the tracker to get a list of
			open issues assigned to you, so that you can pick the issues that
			are being addressed in this commit.
		</para>
		<para>
			Any such interface is of course highly specific to your system,
			so we cannot provide this part, and describing how to create such a
			program is beyond the scope of this manual. The interface definition
			and sample programs can be obtained from the <literal>contrib</literal>
			folder in the
			<ulink url="https://gitlab.com/tortoisegit/tortoisegit/tree/master/contrib/issue-tracker-plugins">
				<citetitle>TortoiseGit repository</citetitle>
			</ulink>.
			(<xref linkend="tgit-preface-source"/> explains how to access the repository).
			A summary of the API is also given in <xref linkend="tgit-ibugtraqprovider"/>

			Another (working) example plugin in C# is
			<ulink url="https://code.google.com/p/gurtle/">
				<citetitle>Gurtle</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			which implements the required COM interface to interact with the
			<ulink url="https://code.google.com/hosting/">
				<citetitle>Google Code</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			issue tracker.
		</para>
		<para>
			For illustration purposes, let's suppose that your system administrator
			has provided you with an issue tracker plugin which you have installed,
			and that you have set up some of your working trees to use the plugin
			in TortoiseGit's settings dialog.
			When you open the commit dialog from a working tree to which the plugin
			has been assigned, you will see a new button at the top of the dialog.
			<figure id="tgit-dug-bugtracker-dia-1">
				<title>Example issue tracker query dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/IssueTrackerQuery.png"/>
			</figure>
			In this example you can select one or more open issues. The plugin
			can then generate specially formatted text which it adds to your log
			message.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
