<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tgit-dug-rename">
	<title>Deleting, Moving and Renaming</title>
	<para>
		Unlike CVS, Git allows renaming and moving of files and
		folders. So there are menu entries for delete and rename
		in the TortoiseGit submenu. However, unlike SVN Git does not track filenames.
		Git only tracks the content of files. So there is in general no need to use the
		Git rename or remove functionality or even to "repair renames" as in SVN. Renames
		and copies are automatically detected when showing the log.
		However, using the Git delete and move functionality the files are automatically
		removed from the Git index (i.e., not shown as missing, but deleted)
		and in case of move/rename also re-added with the new names (i.e., the new names don't show up as unversioned).
		<figure id="tgit-dug-renaming-dia-1">
			<title>Explorer context menu for versioned files</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/ContextMenuFileControl.png"/>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-rename-delete">
		<title>Deleting files and folders</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>delete</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>remove</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			to remove files or folders from Git.
		</para>
		<para>
			When you
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			a file, it is removed from your working tree immediately as well
			as being marked for deletion in the repository on next commit.
<!--
			The file's parent folder shows a <quote>deleted</quote> icon overlay.
-->
			Up until you commit the change, you can get the file back using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			on the parent folder or on the or <xref linkend="tgit-dug-commit"/> or <xref linkend="tgit-dug-wcstatus"/> dialogs.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to delete an item from the repository, but keep it
			locally as an unversioned file/folder, use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Extended Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Delete (keep local)</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You might have to hold the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while right clicking on
			the item in the explorer list pane (right pane) in order to see this
			in the extended context menu.
		</para>
<!--
		<para>
			If a <emphasis>file</emphasis> is deleted via the explorer
			instead of using the TortoiseGit context menu, the commit
			dialog shows those files and lets you remove them from
			version control too before the commit.
			If you need to delete a version-controlled file, always use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice> so that Git doesn't have to guess what
			you really want to do.
		</para>
-->

		<tip>
			<title>Getting a deleted file or folder back</title>
			<para>
				If you have deleted a file or a folder and already committed
				that delete operation to the repository, then a normal
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
				can't bring it back anymore. But the file or folder is not
				lost at all. If you know the revision the file or folder got
				deleted (if you don't, use the log dialog to find out) open
				the repository browser and switch to that revision. Then select
				the file or folder you deleted, right-click and select
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Revert to this revision</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				Refer to <xref linkend="tgit-dug-repobrowser"/> and <xref linkend="tgit-dug-showlog"/> to find out more.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-rename-move">
		<title>Moving files and folders</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>rename</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>move</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_RENAME"?>
		<para>
			If you want to do a simple in-place rename of a file or
			folder, use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Rename...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			Enter the new name for the item and you're done.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to move files around inside your working tree,
			perhaps to a different sub-folder, you can
			use the right-mouse drag-and-drop handler:
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						select the files or directories you want to move
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<action>right-drag</action> them to the
						new location inside the working tree
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						release the right mouse button
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						in the popup menu select
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Git Move versioned files here</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<caution>
			<title>Do Not Git Move Submodule</title>
			<para>
				You should <emphasis>not</emphasis> use the TortoiseGit
				<guilabel>Move</guilabel> or <guilabel>Rename</guilabel>
				commands on a folder which has been created using
				<literal>git submodule</literal>.
			</para>
		</caution>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-renameincase">
		<title>Changing case in a filename</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>case change</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_RENAMEINCASE"?>
		<para>
			Making case-only changes to a filename needs special attention,
			because Windows does not honor the filename casing by default.
			Therefore just renaming a file using the rename command of the Explorer is likely not to work.
			It is important to rename it using Git in order to update the index to make it use the new filename.
			Use the <guimenuitem>Rename...</guimenuitem> command in the TortoiseGit submenu.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-rename-case-conflict">
		<title>Dealing with filename case conflicts</title>
		<para>
			If the repository already contains two files with the same name
			but differing only in case (e.g. <filename>TEST.TXT</filename>
			and <filename>test.txt</filename>), you
			will not be able to commit, and only one of them can be checkout
			on a Windows client. Whilst Git (in general) supports case-sensitive
			filenames, Windows does not.
		</para>
		<para>
			This sometimes happens
			when files are committed from a system with a case-sensitive
			file system, like Linux, or when the setting core.ignorecase is set to false (cf. <xref linkend="git-config(1)"/>).
		</para>
		<para>
			In that case, you have to decide which one of them you want to
			keep and delete the other(s) from the repository (or rename the other(s)).
			Easiest way is to do that on a case-sensitive file system, followed by committing and pushing the changes.
			Doing it on Windows requires several steps (and two commits):
		</para>
		<para>
			Solution
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Delete the file in explorer.
						<caution>
							<para>
								Do NOT use the <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
								or the <guimenuitem>Delete (keep local)</guimenuitem> command
								in the TortoiseGit submenu!
							</para>
						</caution>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Open the Commit dialog.
						(All the checked items are of <literal>Deleted</literal> status.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Un-check only one item you want to keep.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Commit the changes.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Revert deletion of the wanted file in order to get it back. If you want to keep both or more files which had the "same" name, but with a different new name, do this for all files in question and rename them before proceeding with the next file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tgit-dug-rename-del-unversioned">
		<title>Deleting Unversioned Files</title>
		<para>
			Usually you set your ignore list such that all generated files are ignored
			in Git. But what if you want to clear all those ignored items to produce
			a clean build? Usually you would set that in your makefile, but if you are
			debugging the makefile, or changing the build system it is useful to have a way
			of clearing the decks.
		</para>
		<para>
			TortoiseGit provides just such an option using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Extended Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Clean up...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You may have to hold the <keycap>Shift</keycap> while right clicking on a folder
			in the explorer list pane (right pane) in order to see this in the
			context menu.
			This will show a dialog which lists all possible clean up options (cf. <xref linkend="tgit-dug-cleanup"/>).
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
