<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-main">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSMAIN"?>
	<title>General Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>sounds</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-main">
			<title>The Settings Dialog, General Page</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsMain.png"/>
		</figure>
		This dialog allows you to specify your preferred language,
		and the Subversion-specific settings.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Language</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Selects your user interface language.
					What else did you expect?
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Automatically check for newer versions every week</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If checked, TortoiseGit will contact its download site once a week 
					to see if there is a newer version of the program available.
					Use <guibutton>Check now</guibutton> if you want an answer
					right away. The new version will not be downloaded; you
					simply receive an information dialog telling you that the
					new version is available.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>System sounds</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseGit has three custom sounds which are installed by default.
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Error
							</para>
							</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Notice
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Warning
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					You can select different sounds (or turn these sounds
					off completely) using the Windows Control Panel.
					<guibutton>Configure</guibutton> is a shortcut to the Control Panel.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Global ignore pattern</term>
			<listitem>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>exclude pattern</primary>
				</indexterm>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>global ignore</primary>
				</indexterm>
				<para>
					Global ignore patterns are used to prevent unversioned files from
					showing up e.g. in the commit dialog. Files matching the
					patterns are also ignored by an import.
					Ignore files or directories by typing in the names or extensions.
					Patterns are separated by spaces e.g.
					<literal>bin obj *.bak *.~?? *.jar *.[Tt]mp</literal>.
					These patterns should not include any path separators. Note also
					that there is no way to differentiate between files and directories.
					Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-ignore-glob"/> for more information
					on the pattern-matching syntax.
				</para>
				<para>
					Note that the ignore patterns you specify here will also
					affect other Subversion clients running on your PC, including
					the command line client.
				</para>
				<caution>
					<para>
					If you use the Subversion configuration file to set
					a <literal>global-ignores</literal> pattern, it will
					override the settings you make here. The Subversion
					configuration file is accessed using the
					<guibutton>Edit</guibutton> as described below.
					</para>
				</caution>
				<para>
					This ignore pattern will affect all your projects.
					It is not versioned, so it will not affect other users.
					By contrast you can also use the versioned
					<literal>svn:ignore</literal> property to exclude
					files or directories from version control. Read
					<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-ignore"/>
					for more information.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Set file dates to the <quote>last commit time</quote></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This option tells TortoiseGit to set the file dates to
					the last commit time when doing a checkout or an update.
					Otherwise TortoiseGit will use the current date.
					If you are developing software it is generally best
					to use the current date because build systems normally
					look at the date stamps to decide which files need
					compiling. If you use <quote>last commit time</quote> and revert
					to an older file revision, your project may not compile
					as you expect it to.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Subversion configuration file</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Use <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> to edit the 
					Subversion configuration file directly.
					Some settings cannot be modified directly by 
					TortoiseGit, and need to be set here instead.
					For more information about the Subversion 
					<filename>config</filename> file see the 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.confarea.html">
						<citetitle>Runtime Configuration Area</citetitle>
					</ulink>.
					The section on 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.props.html#svn.advanced.props.auto">
						<citetitle>Automatic Property Setting</citetitle>
					</ulink>
					is of particular interest, and that is configured here.
					Note that Subversion can read configuration information
					from several places, and you need to know which one
					takes priority. Refer to 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.confarea.html#svn.advanced.confarea.windows-registry">
						<citetitle>Configuration and the Windows Registry</citetitle>
					</ulink> to find out more.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Use <filename>_svn</filename> instead of <filename>.svn</filename> directories</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					VS.NET when used with web projects can't handle the <literal>.svn</literal>
					folders that Subversion uses to store its internal information.
					This is not a bug in Subversion. The bug is in VS.NET and the frontpage
					extensions it uses. Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings-asp-dot-net"/>
					to find out more about this issue.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to change the behaviour of Subversion and TortoiseGit,
					you can use this checkbox to set the environment variable which
					controls this.
				</para>
				<para>
					You should note that changing this option will not automatically
					convert existing working copies to use the new admin directory.
					You will have to do that yourself using a script (See our FAQ)
					or simply check out a fresh working copy.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-settings-look-feel">
		<title>Context Menu Settings</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSLOOKANDFEEL"?>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-context">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Context Menu Page</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsContext.png"/>
			</figure>
			This page allows you to specify which of the TortoiseGit context menu
			entries will show up in the main context menu, and which will appear
			in the TortoiseGit submenu. By default most items are unchecked and
			appear in the submenu.
		</para>
		<para>
			There is a special case for <guilabel>Get Lock</guilabel>. You can of
			course promote it to the top level using the list above, but as most
			files don't need locking this just adds clutter. However, a file with
			the <literal>svn:needs-lock</literal> property needs this action every
			time it is edited, so in that case it is very useful to have at the top
			level. Checking the box here means that when a file is selected which has
			the <literal>svn:needs-lock</literal> property set,
			<guilabel>Get Lock</guilabel> will always appear at the top level.
		</para>
		<para>
			If there are some paths on your computer where you just don't want
			TortoiseGit's context menu to appear at all, you can list them in
			the box at the bottom.
		</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-settings-dialogs">
		<title>TortoiseGit Dialog Settings 1</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSDIALOGS"?>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-dialogs">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Dialogs 1 Page</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsDialog.png"/>
			</figure>
			This dialog allows you to configure some of TortoiseGit's
			dialogs the way you like them.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Default number of log messages</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Limits the number of log messages that TortoiseGit
						fetches when you first select
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Show Log</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						Useful for slow server connections. You can always use
						<guibutton>Show All</guibutton> or
						<guibutton>Next 100</guibutton> to get more messages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Font for log messages</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Selects the font face and size used to display the log
						message itself in the middle pane of the Revision Log
						dialog, and when composing log messages in the Commit
						dialog.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Short date / time format in log messages</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If the standard long messages use up too much 
						space on your screen use the short format.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Can double-click in log list to compare with previous revision</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If you frequently find yourself comparing revisions in the top
						pane of the log dialog, you can use this option to allow that
						action on double-click. It is not enabled by default because
						fetching the diff is often a long process, and many people
						prefer to avoid the wait after an accidental double-click,
						which is why this option is not enabled by default.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Progress Dialog</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						TortoiseGit can automatically close all progress dialogs 
						when the action is finished without error. This setting
						allows you to select the conditions for closing the
						dialogs. The default (recommended) setting is
						<guilabel>Close manually</guilabel>
						which allows you to review all messages and check what
						has happened. However, you may decide that you want to
						ignore some types of message and have the dialog
						close automatically if there are no critical changes.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Auto-close if no merges, adds or deletes</guilabel>
						means that the progress dialog will close if there were
						simple updates, but if changes from the repository were
						merged with yours, or if any files were added or deleted,
						the dialog will remain open. It will also stay open if
						there were any conflicts or errors during the operation.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Auto-close if no merges, adds or deletes for
						local operations</guilabel> means that the progress dialog
						will close as for <guilabel>Auto-close if no merges, adds
						or deletes</guilabel> but only for local operations like adding
						files or reverting changes. For remote operations the
						dialog will stay open.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Auto-close if no conflicts</guilabel>
						relaxes the criteria further and will close the dialog
						even if there were merges, adds or deletes. However,
						if there were any conflicts or errors, the dialog
						remains open.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Auto-close if no errors</guilabel>
						always closes the dialog even if there were conflicts.
						The only condition that keeps the dialog open is an
						error condition, which occurs when Subversion is unable
						to complete the task. For example, an update fails
						because the server is inaccessible, or a commit fails
						because the working copy is out-of-date.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Use recycle bin when reverting</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you revert local modifications, your changes are
						discarded. TortoiseGit gives you an extra safety net by
						sending the modified file to the recycle bin before
						bringing back the pristine copy. If you prefer to
						skip the recycle bin, uncheck this option.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Use URL of WC as the default <quote>From:</quote> URL</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the merge dialog, the default behaviour is for the
						<guilabel>From:</guilabel> URL to be remembered between
						merges. However, some people like to perform merges from
						many different points in their hierarchy, and find it easier
						to start out with the URL of the current working copy.
						This can then be edited to refer to a parallel path on
						another branch.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Default checkout path</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You can specify the default path for checkouts. If you keep all
						your checkouts in one place, it is useful to have the drive
						and folder pre-filled so you only have to add the new folder name
						to the end.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Default checkout URL</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You can also specify the default URL for checkouts. If you often
						checkout sub-projects of some very large project, it can be useful
						to have the URL pre-filled so you only have to add the sub-project
						name to the end.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-settings-dialogs-2">
		<title>TortoiseGit Dialog Settings 2</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSMISC"?>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-dialogs-2">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Dialogs 2 Page</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsDialog2.png"/>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Recurse into unversioned folders</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If this box is checked (default state), then whenever
						the status of an unversioned folder is shown in the
						<guilabel>Add</guilabel>,
						<guilabel>Commit</guilabel> or
						<guilabel>Check for Modifications</guilabel> dialog,
						every child file and folder is also shown.
						If you uncheck this box, only the unversioned parent is shown.
						Unchecking reduces clutter in these dialogs. In that case if you
						select an unversioned folder for Add, it is added recursively.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Use auto-completion of file paths and keywords</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The commit dialog includes a facility to parse the list
						of filenames being committed. When you type the first 3
						letters of an item in the list, the auto-completion
						box pops up, and you can press Enter to complete the
						filename. Check the box to enable this feature.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Timeout in seconds to stop the auto-completion parsing</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The auto-completion parser can be quite slow if there are a lot
						of large files to check. This timeout stops the commit dialog
						being held up for too long. If you are missing important
						auto-completion information, you can extend the timeout.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Only use spellchecker when <literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> is set</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If you don't wish to use the spellchecker for all commits,
						check this box. The spellchecker will still be enabled where
						the project properties require it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Max. items to keep in the log message history</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you type in a log message in the commit dialog, TortoiseGit
						stores it for possible re-use later. By default it will keep the
						last 25 log messages for each repository, but you can customize
						that number here.
						If you have many different repositories, you may wish to
						reduce this to avoid filling your registry.
					</para>
					<para>
						Note that this setting applies only to messages that you type
						in on this computer. It has nothing to do with the log cache.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Re-open commit and branch/tag dialog after a commit failed</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When a commit fails for some reason (working copy needs updating,
						pre-commit hook rejects commit, network error, etc), you can select
						this option to keep the commit dialog open ready to try again.
						However, you should be aware that this can lead to problems.
						If the failure means you need to update your working copy, and
						that update leads to conflicts you must resolve those first.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Select items automatically</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The normal behaviour in the commit dialog is for all modified
						(versioned) items to be selected for commit automatically.
						If you prefer to start with nothing selected and pick the
						items for commit manually, uncheck this box.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Contact the repository on startup</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The Check for Modifications dialog checks the working copy
						by default, and only contacts the repository when you click
						<guibutton>Check repository</guibutton>. If you always want
						to check the repository, you can use this setting to make that
						action happen automatically.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Show Lock dialog before locking files</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you select one or more files and then use
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>TortoiseGit</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Lock</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						to take out a lock on those files, on some projects it is
						customary to write a lock message explaining why you have
						locked the files. If you do not use lock messages, you can
						uncheck this box to skip that dialog and lock the files
						immediately.
					</para>
					<para>
						If you use the lock command on a folder, you are always
						presented with the lock dialog as that also gives you the
						option to select files for locking.
					</para>
					<para>
						If your project is using the <literal>tsvn:lockmsgminsize</literal>
						property, you will see the lock dialog regardless of this setting
						because the project <emphasis>requires</emphasis> lock messages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="tsvn-dug-settings-colours">
		<title>TortoiseGit Colour Settings</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSCOLORS"?>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-colors">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Colours Page</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsColors.png"/>
			</figure>
			This dialog allows you to configure the text colours
			used in TortoiseGit's dialogs the way you like them.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Possible or real conflict / obstructed</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A conflict has occurred during update, or may occur during merge.
						Update is obstructed by an existing unversioned file/folder of
						the same name as a versioned one.
					</para>
					<para>
						This colour is also used for error messages in the progress dialogs.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Added files</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Items added to the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Missing / deleted / replaced</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Items deleted from the repository, missing from the working
						copy, or deleted from the working copy and replaced with
						another file of the same name.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Merged</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Changes from the repository successfully merged into the WC
						without creating any conflicts.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Modified / copied</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Add with history, or paths copied in the repository.
						Also used in the log dialog for entries which include
						copied items.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Deleted node</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An item which has been deleted from the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Added node</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An item which has been added to the repository, by an add, copy
						or move operation.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Renamed node</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An item which has been renamed within the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Replaced node</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The original item has been deleted and a new item with
						the same name replaces it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect3>
</sect2>
