<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-merge">
	<title>Merging</title>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEWIZARD_START"?>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>merge</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		Where branches are used to maintain separate lines of development,
		at some stage you will want to merge the changes made on one branch
		back into the trunk, or vice versa.
	</para>
	<para>
		It is important to understand how branching and merging works in
		Subversion before you start using it, as it can become quite complex.
		It is highly recommended that you read the chapter
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.branchmerge.html">
			<citetitle>Branching and Merging</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		in the Subversion book, which gives a full description and many 
		examples of how it is used.
	</para>
	<para>
		The next point to note is that merging <emphasis>always</emphasis>
		takes place within a working copy. If you want to merge changes
		<emphasis>into</emphasis> a branch, you have to have a working copy
		for that branch checked out, and invoke the merge wizard from that
		working copy using
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Merge...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
	</para>
	<para>
		In general it is a good idea to perform a merge into an unmodified
		working copy. If you have made other changes in your WC, commit those
		first. If the merge does not go as you expect, you may want to revert
		the changes, and the <guilabel>Revert</guilabel> command will discard
		<emphasis>all</emphasis> changes including any you made before the merge.
	</para>
	<para>
		There are three common use cases for merging which are handled in
		slightly different ways, as described below.
		The first page of the merge wizard asks you to select the method
		you need.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Merge a range of revisions</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This method covers the case when you have made one or more
					revisions to a branch (or to the trunk) and you want to port
					those changes across to a different branch.
				</para>
				<para>
					What you are asking Subversion to do is this:
					<quote>Calculate the changes necessary to get [FROM] revision 1
					of branch A [TO] revision 7 of branch A, and apply those changes
					to my working copy (of trunk or branch B).</quote>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Reintegrate a branch</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This method covers the case when you have made a feature branch
					as discussed in the Subversion book. All trunk changes have been
					ported to the feature branch, week by week, and now the feature
					is complete you want to merge it back into the trunk. Because
					you have kept the feature branch synchronized with the trunk,
					the latest versions of branch and trunk will be absolutely
					identical except for your branch changes.
				</para>
				<para>
					This is a special case of the tree merge described below,
					and it requires only the URL to merge from (normally) your
					development branch. It uses the merge-tracking features of
					Subversion to calculate the correct revision ranges to use,
					and perform additional checks which ensure that the branch has
					been fully updated with trunk changes. This ensures that you don't
					accidentally undo work that others have committed to trunk since
					you last synchronized changes.
				</para>
				<para>
					After the merge, all branch development has been completely
					merged back into the main development line. The branch is now
					redundant and can be deleted.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have performed a reintegrate merge you should not
					continue to use it for development. The reason for this is that
					if you try to resynchronize your existing branch from trunk later on,
					merge tracking will see your reintegration as a trunk change
					that has not yet been merged into the branch, and will try to
					merge the branch-to-trunk merge back into the branch!
					The solution to this is simply to create a new branch from trunk
					to continue the next phase of your development.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Merge two different trees</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This is a more general case of the reintegrate method.
					What you are asking Subversion to do is:
					<quote>Calculate the changes necessary to get [FROM] the head
					revision of the trunk [TO] the head revision of the branch, and
					apply those changes to my working copy (of the trunk).</quote>
					The net result is that trunk now looks exactly like the branch.
				</para>
				<para>
					If your server/repository does not support merge-tracking
					then this is the only way to merge a branch back to trunk.
					Another use case occurs when you are using vendor branches
					and you need to merge the changes following a new vendor drop
					into your trunk code. For more information read the chapter on
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.vendorbr.html">
						<citetitle>vendor branches</citetitle>
					</ulink>
					in the Subversion Book.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-range">
		<title>Merging a Range of Revisions</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEWIZARD_REVRANGE"?>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge</primary>
			<secondary>revision range</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-merge-wizard-range">
				<title>The Merge Wizard - Select Revision Range</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/MergeWizardRange.png"/>
			</figure>
			In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
			folder URL of the branch or tag containing the changes
			you want to port into your working copy.
			You may also click
			<guibutton>...</guibutton>
			to browse the repository and find the desired branch.
			If you have merged from this branch before, then just
			use the drop down list which shows a history of
			previously used URLs.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the <guilabel>Revision range to merge</guilabel> field
			enter the list of revisions you want to merge. This can
			be a single revision, a list of specific revisions
			separated by commas, or a range of revisions separated by a
			dash, or any combination of these.
		</para>
		<important>
			<para>
				There is an important difference in the way a revision
				range is specified with TortoiseSVN compared to the
				command line client. The easiest way to visualise it is
				to think of a fence with posts and fence panels.
			</para>
			<para>
				With the command line client you specify the changes
				to merge using two <quote>fence post</quote> revisions
				which specify the <emphasis>before</emphasis> and
				<emphasis>after</emphasis> points.
			</para>
			<para>
				With TortoiseSVN you specify the changeset to merge
				using <quote>fence panels</quote>. The reason for this
				becomes clear when you use the log dialog to specify
				revisions to merge, where each revision appears as
				a changeset.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you are merging revisions in chunks, the method
				shown in the subversion book will have you merge
				100-200 this time and 200-300 next time. With
				TortoiseSVN you would merge 100-200 this time and
				201-300 next time.
			</para>
			<para>
				This difference has generated a lot of heat on the
				mailing lists. We acknowledge that there is a difference
				from the command line client, but we believe that for the
				majority of GUI users it is easier to understand the
				method we have implemented.
			</para>
		</important>
		<para>
			The easiest way to select the range of revisions you need
			is to click on <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton>, as this
			will list recent changes with their log comments.
			If you want to merge the changes from a single revision, just
			select that revision. If you want to merge changes from several
			revisions, then select that range
			(using the usual <keycap>Shift</keycap>-modifier).
			Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and the list of revision
			numbers to merge will be filled in for you.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to merge changes back <emphasis>out</emphasis>
			of your working copy, to revert a change which has already
			been committed, select the revisions to revert and make sure
			the <guilabel>Reverse merge</guilabel> box is checked.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you have already merged some changes from this branch,
			hopefully you will have made a note of the last revision
			merged in the log message when you committed the change.
			In that case, you can use <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton>
			for the Working Copy to trace that log message.
			Remembering that we are thinking of revisions as
			changesets, you should Use the revision after the
			end point of the last merge as the start point for this
			merge. For example, if you have merged revisions 37 to 39
			last time, then the start point for this merge should be
			revision 40.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are using the merge tracking features of Subversion,
			you do not need to remember which revisions have already been
			merged - Subversion will record that for you. If you leave
			the revision range blank, all revisions which have not yet
			been merged will be included. Read
			<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-merge-tracking"/> to find out more.
		</para>
		<para>
			If other people may be committing changes then be careful
			about using the HEAD revision. It may not refer to the
			revision you think it does if someone else made a commit
			after your last update.
		</para>
		<para>
			Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> and go to
			<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-merge-options"/>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-reintegrate">
		<title>Reintegrate a branch</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEWIZARD_REINTEGRATE"?>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge</primary>
			<secondary>reintegrate</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-merge-wizard-reintegrate">
				<title>The Merge Wizard - Reintegrate Merge</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/MergeWizardReintegrate.png"/>
			</figure>
			To merge a feature branch back into the trunk you must start the
			merge wizard from within a working copy of the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the <guilabel>From URL:</guilabel> field enter the full
			folder URL of the branch that you want to merge back.
			You may also click
			<guibutton>...</guibutton>
			to browse the repository.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are some conditions which apply to a reintegrate merge.
			Firstly, the server must support merge tracking.
			The working copy must be of depth infinite (no sparse checkouts),
			and it must not have any local modifications, switched items or
			items that have been updated to revisions other than HEAD.
			All changes to trunk made during branch development must have
			been merged across to the branch (or marked as having been merged).
			The range of revisions to merge will be calculated automatically.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-tree">
		<title>Merging Two Different Trees</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEWIZARD_TREE"?>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge</primary>
			<secondary>two trees</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-merge-wizard-trees">
				<title>The Merge Wizard - Tree Merge</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/MergeWizardTree.png"/>
			</figure>
			If you are using this method to merge a feature branch back to trunk,
			you need to start the merge wizard from within a working copy of trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
			folder URL of the <emphasis>trunk</emphasis>. This
			may sound wrong, but remember that the trunk is the
			start point to which you want to add the branch changes.
			You may also click
			<guibutton>...</guibutton>
			to browse the repository.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the <guilabel>To:</guilabel> field enter the full
			folder URL of the feature branch.
		</para>
		<para>
			In both the <guilabel>From Revision</guilabel> field and
			the <guilabel>To Revision</guilabel> field, enter the
			last revision number at which the two trees were
			synchronized. If you are sure no-one else is making
			commits you can use the HEAD revision in both cases.
			If there is a chance that someone else may have made
			a commit since that synchronization, use the specific
			revision number to avoid losing more recent commits.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also use <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> to
			select the revision.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-options">
		<title>Merge Options</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEWIZARD_OPTIONS"?>
		<para>
			This page of the wizard lets you specify advanced options,
			before starting the merge process.
			Most of the time you can just use the default settings.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can specify the depth to use for the merge, i.e. how far down
			into your working copy the merge should go. The depth terms used
			are described in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-checkout-depth"/>. The
			default depth is <guilabel>Working copy</guilabel>, which uses
			the existing depth setting, and is almost always what you want.
		</para>
		<para>
			Most of the time you want merge to take account of the file's history,
			so that changes relative to a common ancestor are merged. Sometimes
			you may need to merge files which are perhaps related, but not in
			your repository. For example you may have imported versions 1 and 2 of
			a third party library into two separate directories. Although they
			are logically related, Subversion has no knowledge of this because
			it only sees the tarballs you imported. If you attempt to merge the
			difference between these two trees you would see a complete removal
			followed by a complete add. To make Subversion use only path-based
			differences rather than history-based differences, check the
			<guilabel>Ignore ancestry</guilabel> box. Read more about this 
			topic in the Subversion book,
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.branchmerge.advanced.html#svn.branchmerge.advanced.ancestry">
				<citetitle>Noticing or Ignoring Ancestry</citetitle>
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<para>
			You can specify the way that line ending and whitespace changes are handled.
			These options are described in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-diff-eol-whitespace"/>.
			The default behaviour is to treat all whitespace and line-end differences
			as real changes to be merged.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are using merge tracking and you want to mark a revision as
			having been merged, without actually doing the merge here, check the
			<guilabel>Only record the merge</guilabel> checkbox. There are two
			possible reasons you might want to do this. It may be that the merge
			is too complicated for the merge algorithms, so you code the changes
			by hand, then mark the change as merged so that the merge tracking
			algorithm is aware of it. Or you might want to prevent a particular
			revision from being merged. Marking it as already merged will prevent
			the merge occurring with merge-tracking-aware clients.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now everything is set up, all you have to do is click on the
			<guibutton>Merge</guibutton> button. If you want to preview the results
			<guibutton>Test Merge</guibutton> performs the merge operation, but does
			<emphasis>not</emphasis> modify the working copy at all.
			It shows you a list of the files that will be changed
			by a real merge, and notes those areas where conflicts will occur.
		</para>
		<para>
			The merge progress dialog shows each stage of the merge, with the
			revision ranges involved. This may indicate one more revision than
			you were expecting. For example if you asked to merge revision 123
			the progress dialog will report <quote>Merging revisions 122 through
			123</quote>. To understand this you need to remember that Merge is
			closely related to Diff. The merge process works by generating a list
			of differences between two points in the repository, and applying
			those differences to your working copy. The progress dialog is simply
			showing the start and end points for the diff.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-review">
		<title>Reviewing the Merge Results</title>
		<para>
			The merge is now complete. It's a good idea to have a look at the
			merge and see if it's as expected. Merging is usually quite complicated.
			Conflicts often arise if the branch has drifted far from the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			For Subversion clients and servers prior to 1.5, no merge information
			is stored and merged revisions have to be tracked manually. 
			When you have tested the changes and come to commit this revision,
			your commit log message should <emphasis>always</emphasis>
			include the revision numbers which have been ported in the merge.
			If you want to apply another merge at a later time you will need to
			know what you have already merged, as you do not want to port a
			change more than once. For more information about this, refer to
			<!-- NOTE this reference to the 1.4 book is deliberate. This is the
			     pre-mergetracking stuff which is not covered in version 1.5
			-->
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.4/svn.branchmerge.copychanges.html#svn.branchmerge.copychanges.bestprac">
				<citetitle>Best Practices for Merging</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			in the Subversion book.
		</para>
		<para>
			If your server and all clients are running Subversion 1.5 or higher,
			the merge tracking facility will record the revisions merged and avoid
			a revision being merged more than once. This makes your life much simpler
			as you can simply merge the entire revision range each time and know
			that only new revisions will actually be merged.
		</para>
		<para>
			Branch management is important. If you want to keep this branch up to
			date with the trunk, you should be sure to merge often so that the
			branch and trunk do not drift too far apart. Of course, you
			should still avoid repeated merging of changes, as explained above.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you have just merged a feature branch back into the trunk,
				the trunk now contains all the new feature code, and the
				branch is obsolete. You can now delete it from the repository
				if required.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<important>
			<para>
				Subversion can't merge a file with a folder and vice versa - only
				folders to folders and files to files. If you click on a file and
				open up the merge dialog, then you have to give a path to a file
				in that dialog. If you select a folder and bring up the dialog,
				then you must specify a folder URL for the merge.
			</para>
		</important>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-tracking">
		<title>Merge Tracking</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge tracking</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Subversion 1.5 introduced facilities for merge tracking. When you
			merge changes from one tree into another, the revision numbers merged are
			stored and this information can be used for several different purposes.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You can avoid the danger of merging the same revision twice
						(repeated merge problem). Once a revision is marked as having
						been merged, future merges which include that revision in the
						range will skip over it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you merge a branch back into trunk, the log dialog
						can show you the branch commits as part of the trunk
						log, giving better traceability of changes.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you show the log dialog from within the merge dialog,
						revisions already merged are shown in grey.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When showing blame information for a file, you can choose
						to show the original author of merged revisions, rather than
						the person who did the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You can mark revisions as <emphasis>do not merge</emphasis>
						by including them in the list of merged revisions without
						actually doing the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Merge tracking information is stored in the <literal>svn:mergeinfo</literal>
			property by the client when it performs a merge. When the merge is committed
			the server stores that information in a database, and when you request merge,
			log	or blame information, the server can respond appropriately. For the system
			to work properly you must ensure that the server, the repository and all clients
			are upgraded.
			Earlier clients will not store the <literal>svn:mergeinfo</literal> property
			and earlier servers will not provide the information requested by new clients.
		</para>
		<para>
			Find out more about merge tracking from Subversion's
			<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/merge-tracking/index.html">
				<citetitle>Merge tracking documentation</citetitle>
			</ulink>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-conflict-callback">
		<title>Handling Conflicts during Merge</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_CONFLICTRESOLVE"?>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge conflicts</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Merging does not always go smoothly. Sometimes there is a
			conflict, and if you are merging multiple ranges, you generally
			want to resolve the conflict before merging of the next range
			starts. TortoiseSVN helps you through this process by showing
			the <emphasis>merge conflict callback</emphasis> dialog.
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-merge-callback-dia">
				<title>The Merge Conflict Callback Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/MergeConflictCallback.png"/>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			When a conflict occurs during the merge, you have three ways to
			handle it.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You may decide that your local changes are much more
						important, so you want to discard the version from the
						repository and keep your local version. Or you might
						discard your local changes in favour of the repository
						version. Either way, no attempt is made to merge the
						changes - you choose one or the other.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Normally you will want to look at the conflicts and resolve
						them. In that case, choose the <guibutton>Edit Conflict</guibutton>
						which will start up your merge tool. When you are satisfied with
						the result, click <guibutton>Resolved</guibutton>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The last option is to postpone resolution and continue
						with merging. You can choose to do that for the current
						conflicted file, or for all files in the rest of the merge.
						However, if there are further changes in that file, it
						will not be possible to complete the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you do not want to use this interactive callback, there is a
			checkbox in the merge progress dialog <guilabel>Merge non-interactive</guilabel>.
			If this is set for a merge and the merge would result in a conflict,
			the file is marked as in conflict and the merge goes on. You will have
			to resolve the conflicts after the whole merge is finished.
			If it is not set, then before a file is marked as conflicted you get the
			chance to resolve the conflict <emphasis>during</emphasis> the merge.
			This has the advantage that if a file gets multiple merges (multiple
			revisions apply a change to that file), subsequent merges might succeed
			depending on which lines are affected. But of course you can't walk away
			to get a coffee while the merge is running ;)
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-all">
		<title>Merge a Completed Branch</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGEALL"?>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>merge reintegrate</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			If you want to merge all changes from a feature branch
			back to trunk, then you can use the
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Merge reintegrate...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the extended context menu (hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
			key while you right click on the file).
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-mergeall-dia-1">
				<title>The Merge reintegrate Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/MergeAll.png"/>
			</figure>
			This dialog is very easy. All you have to do is set the options for
			the merge, as described in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-merge-options"/>.
			The rest is done by TortoiseSVN automatically using merge tracking.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-maintenance">
		<title>Feature Branch Maintenance</title>
		<para>
			When you develop a new feature on a separate branch it is a good
			idea to work out a policy for re-integration when the feature is
			complete. If other work is going on in <literal>trunk</literal>
			at the same time you may find that the differences become significant
			over time, and merging back becomes a nightmare.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the feature is relatively simple and development will not take
			long then you can adopt a simple approach, which is to keep
			the branch entirely separate until the feature is complete,
			then merge the branch changes back into trunk. In the merge wizard
			this would be a simple <guilabel>Merge a range of revisions</guilabel>,
			with the revision range being the revision span of the branch.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the feature is going to take longer and you need to account
			for changes in <literal>trunk</literal>, then you need to keep
			the branch synchronised. This simply means that periodically
			you merge trunk changes into the branch, so that the branch
			contains all the trunk changes <emphasis>plus</emphasis> the
			new feature. The synchronisation process uses
			<guilabel>Merge a range of revisions</guilabel>. When the feature
			is complete then you can merge it back to <literal>trunk</literal>
			using either <guilabel>Reintegrate a branch</guilabel> or
			<guilabel>Merge two different trees</guilabel>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
