<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-blame">
	<title>Who Changed Which Line?</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>blame</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>annotate</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>praise</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_BLAME"?>
	<para>
		Sometimes you need to know not only what lines have changed, but also
		who exactly changed specific lines in a file. That's when the
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Blame...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		command, sometimes also referred to as <firstterm>annotate</firstterm>
		command comes in handy.
	</para>
	<para>
		This command lists, for every line in a file, the author and the revision
		the line was changed.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-blame-simple">
		<title>Blame for Files</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-blame-dia-1">
				<title>The Annotate / Blame Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/BlameDialog.png"/>
			</figure>
			If you're not interested in changes from earlier revisions you can
			set the revision from which the blame should start. Set this to <literal>1</literal>,
			if you want the blame for <emphasis>every</emphasis> revision.
		</para>
		<para>
			By default the blame file is viewed using <firstterm>TortoiseBlame</firstterm>,
			which highlights the different revisions to make it easier to read.
			If you wish to print or edit the blame file, select
			<guilabel>Use Text viewer to view blames</guilabel>
		</para>
		<para>
			You can specify the way that line ending and whitespace changes are handled.
			These options are described in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-diff-eol-whitespace"/>.
			The default behaviour is to treat all whitespace and line-end differences
			as real changes, but if you want to ignore an indentation change and find
			the original author, you can choose an appropriate option here.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once you press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> TortoiseSVN starts retrieving
			the data to create the blame file. Please note: This can take several
			minutes to finish, depending on how much the file has changed and
			of course your network connection to the repository. Once the blame
			process has finished the result is written into a temporary file and
			you can view the results.
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-blame-dia-2">
				<title>TortoiseBlame</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/TortoiseBlame.png"/>
			</figure>
			TortoiseBlame, which is included with TortoiseSVN, makes the blame file
			easier to read. When you hover the mouse over a line in the blame info
			column, all lines with the same revision are shown with a darker
			background. Lines from other revisions which were changed by the same author
			are shown with a light background.
			The colouring may not work as clearly if you have your display set to
			256 colour mode.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you <action>left click</action>
			on a line, all lines with the same revision are highlighted, and lines from
			other revisions by the same author are highlighted in a lighter colour.
			This highlighting is sticky, allowing you to move the mouse without losing
			the highlights. Click on that revision again to turn off highlighting.
		</para>
		<para>
			The revision comments (log message) are shown in a hint box whenever
			the mouse hovers over the blame info column. If you want to copy the
			log message for that revision, use the context menu which appears when
			you right click on the blame info column.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can search within the Blame report using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Find...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			This allows you to search for revision numbers, authors and the content of
			the file itself. Log messages are not included in the search - you should
			use the Log Dialog to search those.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also jump to a specific line number using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Go To Line...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
		</para>
		<para>
			When the mouse is over the blame info columns, a context menu is
			available which helps with comparing revisions and examining history,
			using the revision number of the line under the mouse as a reference.
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Blame previous revision</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice> generates a blame report for the same file, but using
			the previous revision as the upper limit. This gives you the blame
			report for the state of the file just before the line you are looking
			at was last changed.
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Show changes</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice> starts your diff viewer, showing you what changed in
			the referenced revision.
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Show log</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice> displays the revision log dialog starting with the
			referenced revision.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you need a better visual indicator of where the oldest and newest
			changes are, select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Color age of lines</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			This will use a colour gradient to show newer lines in red and older lines
			in blue. The default colouring is quite light, but you can change it using
			the TortoiseBlame settings.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are using Merge Tracking, where lines have changed as a result of
			merging from another path, TortoiseBlame will show the revision and author
			of the last change in the original file rather than the revision where the
			merge took place. These lines are indicated by showing the revision and
			author in italics.
			If you do not want merged lines shown in this way, uncheck the
			<guilabel>Include merge info</guilabel> checkbox.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to see the paths involved in the merge, select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Merge paths</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The settings for TortoiseBlame can be accessed using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Settings...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			on the TortoiseBlame tab. Refer to 
			<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings-tortoiseblame"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-blame-diffs">
		<title>Blame Differences</title>
		<para>
			One of the limitations of the Blame report is that it only shows the file as
			it was in a particular revision, and shows the last person to change each line.
			Sometimes you want to know what change was made, as well as who made it. What
			you need here is a combination of the diff and blame reports.
		</para>
		<para>
			The revision log dialog includes several options which allow you to do this.
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Blame Revisions</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							In the top pane, select 2 revisions, then select
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Blame revisions</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>.
							This will fetch the blame data for the 2 revisions, then
							use the diff viewer to compare the two blame files.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Blame Changes</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Select one revision in the top pane, then pick one file
							in the bottom pane and select
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Blame changes</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>.
							This will fetch the blame data for the selected revision
							and the previous revision, then use the diff viewer to
							compare the two blame files.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Compare and Blame with Working BASE</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Show the log for a single file, and in the top pane, select
							a single revision, then select
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Compare and Blame with Working BASE</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>.
							This will fetch the blame data for the selected revision,
							and for the file in the working BASE, then use the diff
							viewer to compare the two blame files.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
