<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-network">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSPROXY"?>
	<title>Network Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>proxy server</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-4">
			<title>The Settings Dialog, Network Page</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsProxy.png"/>
		</figure>
		Here you can configure your proxy server, if you need one to get
		through your company's firewall.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you need to set up per-repository proxy settings, you will
		need to use the Subversion <filename>servers</filename> file to
		configure this. Use <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> to get there
		directly. Consult the
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.confarea.html">
			<citetitle>Runtime Configuration Area</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		for details on how to use this file.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can also specify which program TortoiseGit should use to
		establish a secure connection to a svn+ssh repository.
		We recommend that you use TortoisePlink.exe. This is a version
		of the popular Plink program, and is included with TortoiseGit,
		but it is compiled as a Windowless app, so you don't get a DOS
		box popping up every time you authenticate.
	</para>
	<para>
		You must specify the full path to the executable. For TortoisePlink.exe
		this is the standard TortoiseGit bin directory. Use the
		<guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to help locate it.
		Note that if the path contains spaces, you must enclose it in quotes,
		e.g.
<screen>
"C:\Program Files\TortoiseGit\bin\TortoisePlink.exe"
</screen>
	</para>
	<para>
		One side-effect of not having a window is that there is
		nowhere for any error messages to go, so if authentication
		fails you will simply get a message saying something like
		<quote>Unable to write to standard output</quote>.
		For this reason we recommend that you first set up using
		standard Plink. When everything is working, you can use
		TortoisePlink with exactly the same parameters.
	</para>
	<para>
		TortoisePlink does not have any documentation of its own because it
		is just a minor variant of Plink. Find out about command line
		parameters from the
		<ulink url="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/">
			<citetitle>PuTTY website</citetitle>
		</ulink>
	</para>
	<para>
		To avoid being prompted for a password repeatedly, you might also
		consider using a password caching tool such as Pageant. This is also
		available for download from the PuTTY website.
	</para>
	<para>
		Finally, setting up SSH on server and clients is a non-trivial process
		which is beyond the scope of this help file. However, you can find a
		guide in the TortoiseGit FAQ listed under
		<ulink url="http://TortoiseGit.net/ssh_howto">
			<citetitle>Subversion/TortoiseGit SSH How-To</citetitle>
		</ulink>.
	</para>
</sect2>
