<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tmerge-dug-conflicts">
	<title>Merging / Editing Conflicts</title>
	<para>
		TortoiseGitMerge not only <emphasis>shows</emphasis> you the differences
		between files but also lets you resolve conflicts or apply changes.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you're in two pane view, then you can only edit the file in the
		right pane (<literal>Mine</literal>). To apply changes made in the
		left file (<literal>Theirs</literal>),
		<action>right click</action> on the changed lines and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Use text block from 'theirs'
			</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		Then the changes from the left file are added to the right file.
	</para>
	<para>
		Sometimes you actually want both text blocks, and the context menu
		also offers you
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Use both text blocks (this one first)</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		and
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Use both text blocks (this one last)</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can also edit the output file just as you would in a
		text editor. Such lines are marked using a pencil icon.
		Please note that if you want to make any of the line/block-based changes
		described above, it is better to do those first since once you start
		editing the file yourself it becomes impossible for TortoiseGitMerge to
		keep track of the relationship to the original files.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you're in three pane view (sometimes called
		<emphasis>merge view</emphasis>) you can only edit the file in the
		bottom view (<literal>Merged</literal>). As in two pane view,
		you can <action>right click</action> on conflicted
		lines and either select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Use text block from 'theirs'
			</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		or
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Use text block from 'mine'
			</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		In addition, if you want <emphasis>both</emphasis> blocks, you can
		select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>
				Use text block from 'mine' before 'theirs'
			</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		or
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>
				Use text block from 'theirs' before 'mine'
			</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		According to the command you've selected, the changes are used
		in the resulting <literal>Merged</literal> file.
	</para>
	<para>
		Sometimes a file will be marked as conflicted in Git, yet when
		you view it using TortoiseGitMerge there are no conflicts shown. This may
		be due to the whitespace handling you have chosen. If you choose to
		ignore line-endings or whitespace changes, those lines will be marked
		using the <emphasis>Conflict-Ignored</emphasis> icon. To resolve the
		conflict you still need to pick which version you want to use.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			Note that if you use TortoiseGitMerge on the same files again,
			any changes to your working copy, whether in TortoiseGitMerge,
			or by hand-editing, <emphasis>will be discarded</emphasis>
			and the file will appear as it did when conflict-editing
			first started.
		</para>
	</important>
</sect1>
