<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tmerge-dug-views">
	<title>Viewing Modes</title>
	<para>
		TortoiseGitMerge has three main viewing modes: one-pane, two-pane
		and three-pane view. One/two-pane view is used to view changes
		and three-pane view is used to resolve conflicts.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tmerge-dug-view-merge">
		<title>Viewing / Merging</title>
		<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-1pane">
			<title>One Pane View</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/TMerge_OnePane.png"/>
		</figure>
		<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-2pane">
			<title>Two Pane View</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/TMerge_TwoPane.png"/>
		</figure>
		<para>
			The two pane view has some features which are not available
			in the one pane view:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Changes inside the modified lines are shown in different
						colors. Added string parts are shown with a lighter color,
						but you can of course configure the colors used here.
						Removed parts are indicated with a dark brown vertical
						line in the string. Check out the screenshot above to
						see how this works.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Code reorganization usually means a lot of changes in whitespaces
						(space, tab, newlines) but no actual code change. For example,
						you split up a very long line into several lines, or you sometimes
						compact several lines together into one.
					</para>
					<para>
						Such changes are marked with a white circle symbol on the left side
						of the views. If you see such a white circle, you know immediately
						that no real code change is there and you don't have to check the
						changed block further.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Hand editing of the file in the right pane is possible in two-pane
						view. Such changes are marked with a pencil symbol.
						Hand editing of the file in the left pane is also possible, only
						when <guibutton>Enable Edit </guibutton> is pressed when the left
						pane is active.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to compare/merge three files, TortoiseGitMerge
			will show you the differences in a three pane view. This view
			is also used if you need to resolve conflicted files.
		</para>
		<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-3pane">
			<title>Three Pane View</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/TMerge_ThreePane.png"/>
		</figure>
		<para>
			The left pane shows you the differences between
			<emphasis>Their</emphasis> file and the <emphasis>Base</emphasis>
			file, while the right pane shows you the differences between
			<emphasis>Mine</emphasis> file and the <emphasis>Base</emphasis>
			file. The bottom pane shows you the result of merging
			<emphasis>Base</emphasis>, <emphasis>Mine</emphasis> and
			<emphasis>Theirs</emphasis> with possible conflicts.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you hover the mouse over the pane title, a tooltip will
			show the filenames used for the diff in each pane.
		</para>
		<para>
			Hand editing of the file in the left pane or right pane is also possible, only
			when <guibutton>Enable Edit </guibutton> is pressed when that pane is active.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tmerge-dug-view-patch">
		<title>Applying Patches</title>
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_FILEPATCHES"?>
		<para>
			After TortoiseGitMerge parses the patch file it will show
			you a small window with all the files which have changes
			according to the patch file.
			<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-patch">
				<title>Patch File List</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/TMerge_PatchWindow.png"/>
			</figure>
			If the filename is shown in black, then the patch can be applied
			without any problems. That means the file is not outdated
			according to the patch.
			However, if the filename is shown in red, then the patch can't
			get applied directly because you already changed that file.
		</para>
		<para>
			The patch file window has a context menu which allows you to
			preview the effect of the patch on the current file
			(apply without saving), to apply and save the changes
			for the selected file, or to apply and save changes to
			<emphasis>all</emphasis> files in the list.
			The double click action is to preview.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
