<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tmerge-dug-toolbar">
	<title>Buttons and Other Controls</title>
	<para>
		<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-toolbar">
			<title>The Toolbar</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/TMerge_Toolbar.png"/>
		</figure>
		Below the menu bar lies the tool bar. This provides easy access to
		the most commonly used tools, which are
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Open</guibutton>
					accesses the file-open dialog. What else?
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Save</guibutton>
					saves any changes you have made.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Reload</guibutton>
					discards any changes you have made in TortoiseMerge and
					reloads the files from disk.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Undo</guibutton>
					implements a multi-level undo, allowing you to reverse
					any changes you have made within TortoiseMerge.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Prev/Next Difference</guibutton>
					jumps directly to the next point where the files differ.
					This saves scrolling through all the unchanged parts
					of the file.
				</para>
				<para>
					When you do this in 2-pane diff mode, the detail bar at
					the bottom of the screen will show you the inline differences
					for the first line, regardless of where the mouse is hovering.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Prev/Next Conflict</guibutton>
					jumps directly to the next point where the file
					differences are in conflict and need to be resolved.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Use Theirs/Use Mine</guibutton>
					selects whether to use a block from the left
					or the right pane.
					Refer to the next section for more information about
					editing changes and conflicts.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Theirs before Mine/Mine before Theirs</guibutton>
					is used when you want to combine changes in a conflicted file.
					Refer to the next section for more information about
					editing changes and conflicts.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Mark as Resolved</guibutton>
					When you have resolved all the conflicts in a file and
					saved the changes, you can mark it as resolved from
					within TortoiseMerge, rather than going back to
					explorer and marking as resolved from there.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Show Whitespaces</guibutton>
					toggles the option to display space and tab characters
					as symbols so you can distinguish white space changes.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Inline Diff Word-wise</guibutton>
					toggles the method used to display inline diffs.
					In word-wise mode, when a character is changed, the whole
					word is highlighted. In char-wise mode, each individual
					changed character is highlighted.
				</para>
				<para>
					Word-wise is the default and in most cases it works better.
					For example if you change a variable name, the whole name
					is highlighted in word-wise mode, whereas in char-wise mode
					you tend to get a mess of added and deleted characters
					which doesn't make much sense. However, some content does
					not resolve neatly into words, for example a hex file,
					and in that case, char-wise display works better.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Switch View</guibutton>
					selects between one-pane and two-pane view.
					Disabled in 3-pane view.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Switch Left and Right View</guibutton>
					In 2-pane view, swaps the left and right windows.
					When you are comparing a file in 2 different trees, 
					as opposed to 2 revisions of the same file, TortoiseSVN
					does not know which one should go in the left pane as
					the <quote>original/base</quote> version. If it gets
					this wrong, you can change it to make viewing easier.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Show/Hide Patch List</guibutton>
					When TortoiseMerge has a patch list, this button allows
					you to hide it (so you can see both windows), or show it
					(so you can review the file list).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<guibutton>Settings</guibutton>
					takes you to TortoiseMerge's settings dialog.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		On the left side of the window is a locator bar. This provides
		a quick visual reference as to where the changes lie within the
		file. The bar has three columns. The left column refers to the
		left pane, the right column to the right pane, and the centre
		column to the bottom pane (if present). In one-pane view only
		the left column is used. The locator bar can also be used as a
		scroll bar to scroll all the windows simultaneously.
	</para>
	<para>
		Below the bottom window is the status bar. This shows the number of
		lines added and deleted in <literal>Theirs</literal> and
		<literal>Mine</literal>, and the number of unresolved
		conflicts remaining.
		You can also see which line-ending style is in use, what
		encoding (ASCII, UTF-8, etc) is assumed by TortoiseMerge, and whether
		there is a byte-order-mark (BOM) present in UTF-8 files.
		The left side of the status bar is used to display hints when you
		hover the mouse over a control.
	</para>
</sect1>
