<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tmerge-dug-toolbar">
	<title>Buttons and Other Controls</title>
	<para>
		Depending on your setting, you either see a toolbar or a ribbon
		with many buttons. The buttons all show a tooltip explaining their
		function when you hover the mouse pointer over them.
	</para>
	<para>
		On the left side of the window is a locator bar. This provides
		a quick visual reference as to where the changes lie within the
		file. The bar has three columns. The left column refers to the
		left pane, the right column to the right pane, and the centre
		column to the bottom pane (if present). In one-pane view only
		the left column is used. The locator bar can also be used as a
		scroll bar to scroll all the windows simultaneously.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you double click on a word then every occurrence of that word will
		be highlighted throughout the document, both in the main panes and the
		locator bar. Double click on the word again to remove the highlighting.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you click in the left margin, or if you triple click within a line,
		that whole line will be selected.
	</para>
	<para>
		Below the bottom window is the status bar. This shows the number of
		lines added and deleted in <literal>Theirs</literal> and
		<literal>Mine</literal>, and the number of unresolved
		conflicts remaining.
	</para>
	<para>
		The status bar also contains combo box controls which indicate how the
		files are handled and treated:
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Encoding</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The encoding specifies how the characters in the views are
						loaded/saved and shown. The most common encoding in English is
						ASCII (which means the local encoding of the OS language), but
						you can change this to be UTF8, UTF16LE, UTF16BE, UTF32LE and
						UTF32BE, both with or without a byte order mark (BOM).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Line Endings</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The most common line endings on Windows is CRLF, but you can
						change the line endings to whatever you like. Note that if you
						change the line endings, then <emphasis>all</emphasis> line
						endings in the whole file will change, even if when loaded the
						line endings were not all the same.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Tabs</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The option at the top of the combo box menu indicates whether
						tabs or spaces are inserted when you press the tab key.
						The <emphasis>smart tab char</emphasis> option if enabled uses
						an algorithm to determine whether one or the other is best used.
					</para>
					<para>
						The tab size specifies how many space chars are inserted when
						editing and pressing the tab char, or how many chars the next
						word is indented when a tab char is encountered.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
</sect1>
