<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="tmerge-basics">
	<title>Basic Concepts</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
			TortoiseGitMerge has several different uses:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Viewing the difference between two files and merging
						changes into one of them, or removing unwanted changes.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Editing conflicts between local changes and changes in the
						Git repository following an update.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Applying patch files and reviewing them.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<sect1 id="tmerge-basics-diff">
		<title>Viewing and Merging Differences</title>
		<para>
			In this mode you are comparing two files. The file in the left pane
			is considered to be the original file (sometimes referred to as
			<emphasis>Theirs</emphasis>, and the file in the right pane is the
			modified file (sometimes referred to as <emphasis>Mine</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can make simple line-based changes to the file in the right pane
			which include:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Reverting changed lines back to the text shown in the left pane.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Using a combination of both blocks, either
						<emphasis>Theirs</emphasis> before <emphasis>Mine</emphasis> or
						<emphasis>Mine</emphasis> before <emphasis>Theirs</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also edit the file in the right pane just as you would in a
			text editor. Such lines are marked using a pencil icon.
			Please note that if you want to make any of the line/block-based changes
			described above, it is better to do those first since once you start
			editing the file yourself it becomes impossible for TortoiseGitMerge to
			keep track of the relationship to the original files.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tmerge-basics-conflicts">
		<title>Editing Conflicts</title>
		<para>
			This is sometimes referred to as a three-way merge, and is shown in three panes.
			However there are actually four files involved. The file which is not shown is
			the common base file, the last common ancestor of the two files which are now
			in conflict. The relationships between the three files are explained in
			the diagram below:
		</para>
		<figure id="tmerge-dug-dia-conflict">
			<title>File Conflict</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/mergeprinciple.png"/>
		</figure>
		<para>
			The base file represents the oldest version of a file, from
			where <emphasis>You</emphasis> and <emphasis>They</emphasis> start
			making changes. <emphasis>Mine</emphasis> represents
			the base file with all the changes <emphasis>you</emphasis> made,
			and <emphasis>Theirs</emphasis> is the file with all the changes
			<emphasis>someone else</emphasis> made to the file.
			The left pane shows the changes in <emphasis>Theirs</emphasis>
			relative to the base file and the right pane shows the changes in
			<emphasis>Mine</emphasis> relative to the base file. The bottom pane is the
			output file which is where you are trying to resolve the conflicts.
		</para>
		<para>
			In conflict resolution view, you can choose to use blocks from
			<emphasis>Mine</emphasis> or <emphasis>Theirs</emphasis> or both.
			But in this case, the changes are shown in the bottom pane.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="tmerge-basics-patch">
		<title>Applying Patches</title>
		<para>
			A patch file is a Git or Subversion unified diff file, which contains
			the information required to apply changes to a set of files.
			The patch may have been supplied by another developer so that you
			can see changes he has made and possibly commit them to the repository.
			Or it may have been generated internally by TortoiseGit when comparing
			two folders. This happens when you compare a repository revision with
			your working copy folder, or if you compare two different repository
			revisions, or if you compare two different repository paths.
		</para>
		<para>
			In either case TortoiseGitMerge will show a small window listing the
			files included in the patch. By double clicking on one of these files
			you fetch the relevant file and apply the changes. The left pane shows
			the original file content and the right pane shows it after the patch
			is applied.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can edit the file in the right pane exactly as you would in
			compare/edit mode.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
